<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Samaritanism reviv'd, a sermon preached at the parish church of Great Yarmouth, upon the ninth of September being the day appointed for a solemn thanksgiving for the discovery of the late horrid plot, against His Majesty's person and government / by Luke Milbourne.</title>
            <author>Milbourne, Luke, 1649-1720.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 146 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50843</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2037</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7778</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12921600</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12921600</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95396</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50843)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95396)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 989:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Samaritanism reviv'd, a sermon preached at the parish church of Great Yarmouth, upon the ninth of September being the day appointed for a solemn thanksgiving for the discovery of the late horrid plot, against His Majesty's person and government / by Luke Milbourne.</title>
                  <author>Milbourne, Luke, 1649-1720.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Roycroft, for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95396:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Samaritaniſm Reviv'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the PARISH CHURCH OF Great Yarmouth, Upon the Ninth of <hi>September;</hi> BEING THE DAY Appointed for a Solemn THANKSGIVING FOR THE Diſcovery of the late Horrid PLOT, againſt His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Perſon and Government.</p>
            <p>By <hi>L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE MILBO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Roycroft,</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhops-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95396:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95396:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE WILLIAM EARL OF Yarmouth, BARON <hi>PASTON</hi> of <hi>PASTON,</hi> HIGH STEWARD OF HIS MAJESTIES BURGH OF <hi>GREAT YARMO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Innocence of the Clergy of our Church, as by Law Eſtabliſh'd, whatever their Pretences are to the Contrary, is indeed the greateſt Scandal and moſt real Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the ſeveral Diſſenting Parties.</p>
            <p>While the Vices of a Clergy-man are Notorious, Hypocrites have ſomewhat to amuſe the Vulgar with,
<pb facs="tcp:95396:3"/>when they live within the Rules of the Church, <hi>thoſe of the Contrary Parties are</hi> conſequently <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed, as having no Evil thing to ſay of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that Shame ſoon breaks out into a Malicious Rage, and where the wiſh'd for Crimes are not to be found, ſome employ themſelves, under the Prince of Hell, to forge Lyes, and affix them boldly, ſew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Men in the Skins of Bears and Wolves, and then expoſing them to be torn in Pieces by Dogs.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Bleſſed Jeſus</hi> met with this Dealing from <hi>Obdurate and Hypocritical Jews,</hi> the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of the Firſt and Pureſt Ages, from <hi>Pagans,</hi> and the <hi>Lawful Clergy</hi> to this day, and in our <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church</hi> meet with it from <hi>pretendedly Pure and Moderate,</hi> but really <hi>Apoſtate Proteſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Veneration with I, upon the moſt unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced and deliberate Study, have entertain'd for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> has made me too a Sharer in that Glory of ſuffering by the Words and Actions of <hi>Ill-Men,</hi> whoſe greateſt Pique againſt me is, That Bad as I am, I am not yet Bad enough to Aſſociate with them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>Ill Will</hi> therefore employs all its Care to trace my Errors, and beſides the Dull and Baſhful Scurrility of <hi>Senſeleſs Libels,</hi> and the utmoſt force of <hi>Belins<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Rhetorick,</hi> it has betray'd it ſelf ſo far, as to declare, that nothing but the Fear of <hi>Humane Laws</hi> ſecur'd my Life.</p>
            <p>This is indeed a very odd Method of <hi>Refining upon Religion,</hi> and perſwading any that Men of
<pb facs="tcp:95396:3"/>ſuch Warm Tempers have attain'd to <hi>Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Degrees of Spirituality;</hi> there was ſo little of this in the Practice of our Saviour and his Apoſtles, and the beſt Chriſtians in all Ages, that for my part, I count it a real <hi>Breach of Charity</hi> and an <hi>Affront to the Goſpel,</hi> to reckon ſuch among the <hi>Proſelytes of Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have to the utmoſt of my Power endeavour'd to advance ſuch Principles as were moſt neceſſary to make Men Truly Good in their ſeveral Relations, <hi>Devout and Pious towards God, Obedient and Submiſſive to their Lawful Superiours, Uniform and Reverend in their Publick Church Services, and Charitable and Peaceable one among an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others have done this better, having carried on that Great Work with Greater Abilities, but none with <hi>Greater Sincerity</hi> or under <hi>Greater Diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements</hi> than my ſelf.</p>
            <p>Had theſe Doctrines been <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally entertain'd, we ſhould have heard of no <hi>Separatiſts or Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, no Plotters, no Traitors, no Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> He deſerves not the Name of a <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel,</hi> who is afraid to ſpeak in the Cauſe of his God and of his King. Never was any Prince the Subject of ſo many Miracles, as Ours; and were not the Sons of <hi>Separation</hi> Mad as well as Blind, He, whom God has ſo oft and wonderfully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, might at length be free from the <hi>Plots of Traitors,</hi> and among the moſt deſperate Villains be believ'd <hi>Invulnerable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:95396:4"/>The <hi>Preachers of Loyalty</hi> might proſecute their Great Maſters Work in Peace; and if the Affection of the Dumb Son of <hi>Croeſus</hi> was to be lov'd and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd, for ſetting his Tongue free to ſave his Royal Fathers Life, the meaneſt Goſpel Miniſter might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſome Favour for ſpeaking Plain, when the <hi>Cruel and Barbarous Hands of Traiterous Hypocrites are lifted up againſt the Dear and Sacred Life of his Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such an Occaſion gave Being to this Diſcourſe which now puts it ſelf under your Honours Protection, and that which bears ſo Great a Name in its Front, muſt be by All concluded Loyal: The Author owns the Weakneſs of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, and therefore the Boldneſs of the Addreſs; but is ſo well acquainted with your Goodneſs, that he dares not doubt of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt Obliged, Moſt Faithful and Obedient Servant, L<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>KE MILBO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95396:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EZRA IV. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Now when the Adverſaries of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> heard that the Children of the Captivity builded the Temple unto the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then they came to <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> and to the chief of the Fathers, and ſaid unto them, Let us build with you, for we ſeek your God as ye do, and we do ſacrifice unto him, ſince the days of <hi>Eſarhaddon</hi> King of <hi>Aſſur,</hi> which brought us up hither.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Jeſhua,</hi> and the reſt of the chief of the Fathers of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid unto them, You have nothing to do with us to build an Houſe unto our God; but we our ſelves will build together unto the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as King <hi>Cyrus</hi> the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> hath commanded us.</p>
                  <p>Then the People of the Land weakned the hands of the People of <hi>Judah,</hi> and troubled them in Building.</p>
                  <p>And hired Counſellors againſt them to fruſtrate their purpoſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>SOLOMON</hi> tells us, that <hi>there is no new thing under the Sun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.9.</note> 
               <hi>for the thing that hath been it is that which ſhall be, and that which is done is that which ſhall be done;</hi> which may give us a good reaſon of what he inſtructs us in elſewhere, <hi>Say not thou,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.10.</note> 
               <hi>What is the cauſe that the former days were better than theſe, for thou doſt not enquire wiſely concerning this.</hi> Which may ſerve as a <hi>Check</hi> to thoſe who are always com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the Times, whereas did they but prudently examine the Records of paſt Ages, they would find the <hi>ſame Evils</hi> prevailing in ſome places heretofore, which they now wonder at as ſuch <hi>new</hi> and <hi>unheard</hi> of things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95396:5"/>The Word of God it ſelf, as it gives us Examples of the greateſt <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> ſo it gives us Inſtances of the moſt <hi>horrid Sins,</hi> ſuch as may ſeem impoſſible to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by the moſt <hi>reprobate Villains</hi> under Heaven; and 'tis our unhappineſs, that the Patterns of the firſt kind are generally paſt by and ſlighted; but even thoſe who make ſome ſlight pretences to goodneſs, are very ſolicitous leſt by their Predeceſſors they ſhould be outdone in Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. So miſerably is the intent of all Records Sacred and Profane perverted, for they are both written for our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, to teach us, that <hi>we ſhould not luſt after evil things,</hi> as we ſind ſome in ſtory have done, and that we ſhould look upon ſuch Hiſtory as written for our <hi>Admonition upon whom the Ends of the World are come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.6.</note> as the Apoſtle adviſes.</p>
            <p>Among the ſeveral Sins Copied out from thoſe Enemies of Religion who liv'd in former Ages, we find none more exactly imitated than thoſe of <hi>Malice, Falſhood and Treachery under the Vail of Zeal and Piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pretended Religion,</hi> in its ſtrongeſt pangs of <hi>Zeal,</hi> has ſo incorporated thoſe Sins into it ſelf, that if Men truly wiſe and pious watch not the more carefully againſt the Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagems of Hell, they may in time be ſo far impos'd upon as to believe it, at leaſt poſſible, for Religion and the moſt abominable Villanies to meet together eaſily in one Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and others to the <hi>Scandal of Chriſtianity</hi> may be ready to imagine Deceit and Baſeneſs the very <hi>Characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtical Notes</hi> of it, and ſo that all the Ill practices charged upon that Profeſſion by the Heathens of Old, were indeed but plain and undeniable Truths. Such a Reputation did the Scribes and Phariſees, thoſe <hi>Monopolizers</hi> of Piety among the <hi>Jews,</hi> bring to their Profeſſion, allowing none but the followers of their bleſſed Examples a portion in the future World,<note place="margin">Matth. 2 3.</note> whilſt our Saviour ſo largely diſcovers what prodigious Impieties their gay Profeſſion was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with.</p>
            <p>If we go further backward we may take notice of theſe <hi>Adverſaries of Judah and Benjamin,</hi> the Subjects of the Text, whoſe <hi>Memory</hi> and <hi>whoſe Practices</hi> we ſee ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving to this day in our <hi>own Nation,</hi> which that we may
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95396:5"/>do the better, I ſhall in my diſcourſe upon theſe words follow this plain and eaſie Method.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. I ſhall explain the Hiſtory of the Text.</item>
               <item>2. I ſhall make Obſervations from it.</item>
               <item>3. I ſhall apply all to our own preſent Caſe.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> For the Explication of the Hiſtory of the Text, I ſhall,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Tell you who theſe Adverſaries of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin</hi> were, with their Conditions, ſo far as Scripture or other Hiſtory has inform'd me.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Salman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſar</hi> King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> had carry'd the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into Captivity, that the Country might not ly wholly deſolate, he placed in it ſeveral Colonies, drawn from other places of his Empire, <hi>viz. from</hi> Babylon,<note place="margin">2 Kings 17.24.</note> 
               <hi>and from</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha, <hi>and from</hi> Ava, <hi>and from</hi> Hamath, <hi>and from</hi> Sepharvaim. From <hi>Babylon,</hi> the Capital City of his Empire, came the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> from <hi>Cutha</hi> the <hi>Cuthaeans,</hi> ſo call'd from the Region of <hi>Chut,</hi> of which name alſo, according to <hi>Joſephus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. lib. 9 c. 14. Selden. Synt. 2. c. &amp;. Bochart. Phal. lib. 3. c. 5.</note> there is a River in <hi>Perſia:</hi> Theſe <hi>Cuthaeans,</hi> as <hi>Bochart</hi> aſſerts, are the ſame with the <hi>Ciſſii</hi> of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Province of <hi>Suſa,</hi> formerly called <hi>Suſiana,</hi> now <hi>Chuſiſtan</hi> on the Eaſt of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Thoſe from <hi>Ava,</hi> called here the <hi>Avites,</hi> the ſame who are elſewhere called <hi>Avims,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Hazerim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 2.23.</note> from whence being driven by the <hi>Caphtorims</hi> or thoſe who came out of <hi>Caphtor,</hi> long before the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> enter'd <hi>Canaan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bochart. Phal. lib. 4. c. 36.</note> they paſt the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> where they found a Seat till this time, when ſome of them were tranſplanted from thence into the former Territories of the Ten Tribes. The next nam'd are the Men of <hi>Hamath,</hi> of whom it may be doubted whether they came from the <hi>Ancient Riblah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.2.</note> call'd by <hi>Amos Hamath the Great,</hi> out of the Ruins of which the famous City of <hi>Antioch</hi> was afterwards rais'd;<note place="margin">Heylin's Coſm. lib. 3. Syria. Zach. 9.2.</note> or which is the more probable from <hi>Epiphania,</hi> call'd alſo <hi>Hamath</hi> a City of <hi>Syria,</hi> not far from the Land of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> from whence a Colony might be more conveniently ſent; it was ſeated according to <hi>Ptolomy</hi> about 80 Miles from the greater <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>math,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ptol. Geogr. lib. 5. c. 15. Bochart. Phal. lib. 4. c. 36. Ferrarius in voce Epiphaniâ.</note> and as much from <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> both of them ſtood on the River <hi>Orontes, Epiphania</hi> near <hi>Lariſſa</hi> in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Caſſiotis,</hi> and was afterwards the Seat of a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95396:6"/>Biſhop</hi> under the <hi>Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Antioch.</hi> The laſt mention'd in the Text are the Men of <hi>Sepharvaim,</hi> of whom I doubt not but they came from the <hi>Sipphara</hi> of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ptol. Geogr. lib. 5. c. 18.</note> ſituate on the <hi>Euphrates</hi> between <hi>Naarda</hi> and <hi>Seleucia,</hi> where it divides, into two branches, ſometime before it meets with the <hi>Tygris,</hi> and ſo not far from <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> it ſelf: And ſo much may ſerve to inform us whence they came.</p>
            <p>For their <hi>Religion,</hi> by which their temper may be very well gueſt at, it was various according to the Cuſtom of thoſe places from whence they came; Scripture informs us that <hi>The men of</hi> Babylon <hi>made</hi> Succoth Benoth,<note place="margin">2 Kings 17.30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>the men of</hi> Cuth <hi>made</hi> Nergal, <hi>and the men of</hi> Hamath <hi>made</hi> Aſhima, <hi>and the</hi> Avites <hi>made</hi> Nibchaz <hi>and</hi> Tartak, <hi>and the</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharvites <hi>burnt their Children in Fire to</hi> Adrammelek <hi>and</hi> Anammelek, <hi>the Gods of</hi> Sepharvaim. What theſe Idols of theirs were may be worth our enquiry.</p>
            <p>The Men of <hi>Babylon</hi> made <hi>Succoth Benoth,</hi> that is, they erected Fanes or Chappels to <hi>Venus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania,</hi> as <hi>Selden</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms us,<note place="margin">Selden. Synt. 2. c. 7. Beyerus in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentis ad cap. 7. p. 314.</note> to which <hi>Beyerus</hi> adds what <hi>Selden</hi> before had rejected, out of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers, that they worſhip'd <hi>a Hen and Chickens,</hi> by which they figured the <hi>Pleiades,</hi> and they were (as he tells us) the Ancient Symbol of the very ſame <hi>Venus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rania;</hi> which fancy of theirs he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes taken from that paſſage of the Spirits <hi>moving</hi> upon the face of the Waters, as we tranſlate it; but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which we render <hi>Moved</hi> is a Metaphorical word, taken from the female Bird covering her Eggs and Young ones gently with her Wings,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Buxtorf. in voce.</note> whereby ſhe ſecures them and nouriſhes them: ſo the Spirit of God covered the Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queous Maſs, and by that gentle incubation made the whole Maſs prolifick, and nouriſht and fomented thoſe Beings which were then in production; and ſo the female Bird makes the Eggs by her incubation fruitful, and afterwards by the ſame guards and cheriſhes her Young ones.</p>
            <p>The Men of <hi>Cuth</hi> made <hi>Nergal,</hi> by the ſame Authors concluded to be <hi>Fire,</hi> the worſhip of which ſacred and <hi>ever burning Fire</hi> was notorious among the <hi>Perſians</hi> from whoſe Country the <hi>Cuthaeans</hi> came;<note place="margin">Selden. Synt. 2. c. 8. &amp; Beyerus in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note> a kind of Idolatry it was which thoſe People were ſo addicted to, that it was no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95396:6"/>uncommon thing for their principal <hi>Devoto's</hi> to caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the ſame Fire there to be conſumed, as an <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary</hi> and very <hi>pleaſing Sacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Men of <hi>Hamath</hi> made <hi>Aſhima,</hi> by which the <hi>Jewiſh Rabbins</hi> commonly underſtand an <hi>He-Goat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Synt. 2. c. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Selden</hi> rejects that Notion of theirs, but declares his own <hi>Ignorance</hi> what it was. <hi>Elias Levita,</hi> as cited by <hi>Beyerus,</hi> ſuppoſes <hi>Aſhima</hi> to have been an <hi>Aſs</hi> or <hi>Monkey,</hi> to which he adds the Cuſtom of ſome <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Arabians</hi> to worſhip that Creature; an Idolatrous practice, as ſome ſay,<note place="margin">Beyerus in add. p. 319. &amp; Linſchoten ibi citatus cum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liis.</note> ſtill follow'd in the Kingdoms of <hi>Pegu</hi> and <hi>Bengala</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt Indies.</hi> But moſt probably it was the figure of <hi>Pan,</hi> horn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, hairy, and cloven footed, and ſo not very unlike an Hee-Goat. This Idol was worſhipt by the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in the ſame manner as among the <hi>Grecians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chartanus de Antiq. Deorum Imaginibus, p. 96.</note> and was by ſome ador'd as the <hi>Symbol of the Sun,</hi> a common Deity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Avites</hi> made <hi>Nibchaz</hi> and <hi>Tartak,</hi> Gods very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure. The <hi>Jewiſh Writers</hi> make <hi>Nibchaz</hi> to be a <hi>Dog,</hi> a Creature worſhip'd by the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> in their <hi>Anubis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Selden Synt. 2. c. 9. &amp; Beyerus in add.</note> to whom though they give a <hi>humane Body</hi> they aſſign the <hi>head of an Hound.</hi> By <hi>Tartak</hi> they underſtand an <hi>Aſs,</hi> of which we meet with no worſhipper in thoſe Ages unleſs the ſame <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> who did <hi>Tot Portenta colere,</hi> might rank it among their Deities. In after times indeed we find <hi>Caecilius</hi> in <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> charging the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with worſhipping the <hi>head of an Aſs;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Minut. Felicis Octavius.</note> a Slander raiſed againſt them from the Doctrine of the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> of whom <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius</hi> tells us, that giving the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to one of their <hi>Celeſtial principalities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius adv. Haer. Gnoſt. p. 91.</note> ſome of them deſcrib'd him under the figure of an <hi>Aſs,</hi> and ſome under that of an <hi>Hog,</hi> either of them Deities ſuitable to the Doctrine and Practices of thoſe <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſtians;</hi> but for their monſtrous Crimes, the true Chriſtians (ſuch was the injuſtice of their Pagan Adverſaries) were forc'd to ſuffer.</p>
            <p>The laſt are the <hi>Sepharvaites,</hi> made <hi>Adrammelech</hi> and <hi>Anammelech,</hi> which again the <hi>Jewiſh Writers,</hi> that they may the better expoſe the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> tell us were an <hi>Horſe</hi> and a <hi>Mule,</hi> others a <hi>Peacock</hi> and a <hi>Quail.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Synt. 1. c. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Selden</hi> takes them to be but two Names for one things, and both to be the ſame with <hi>Moloch</hi> the Abomination of the <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95396:7"/>under which name the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> worſhipt <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</hi> Concerning the <hi>Humane Sacrifices</hi> to which Idol there are different Conjectures, for ſome from the ſtories of <hi>Ahaz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 16.3. Ch. 17.17. RR. Salom. Jac. D. Kimchi. Moſes Mikotzi apud Seldenum.</note> and others making their Sons and their Daughters paſs through the Fire, conclude that the ſacrificing their Children, was only a <hi>Conſecration</hi> of them to that Idol's ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice by ſuch a <hi>luſtration.</hi> But others, amongſt whom <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> himſelf truly agree, That they <hi>burnt their Children to Moloch</hi> in good earneſt, and with that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are charged, that <hi>they ſacrificed their Sons and their Daughters unto Devils,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106.37.</note> 
               <hi>and ſhed innocent blood, even the Blood of their Sons and of their Daughters, whom they ſacrificed unto the Idols of</hi> Canaan; and in the Book of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> the Reaſons being ſum'd up why God had driven out the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Poſſeſſors and ſettled the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Canaan,</hi> among the reſt 'tis added, <hi>They were mercileſs murderers of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, devourers of Mans fleſh and feaſts of Blood;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſdom of Sol. Ch. 12. v. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>The Prieſts out of the midſt of their Idolatrous Crew, and the Parents kill'd with their own hands, Souls deſtitute of help.</hi> Such a ſacrifice as this the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Moab</hi> offer'd in his extremity,<note place="margin">2 Kings 3.27.</note> he offer'd his <hi>eldeſt Son</hi> who ſhould have reign'd after him for a <hi>burnt Offering</hi> upon the Wall. Other Relations we have of the <hi>Brazen Image</hi> of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loch</hi> with its <hi>ſeven Cells,</hi> wherein the <hi>fine Flower,</hi> the <hi>Turtle Doves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Selden ubi ſupr.</note> the <hi>Sheep,</hi> the <hi>Ram,</hi> the <hi>Calf,</hi> the <hi>Ox</hi> and the <hi>Child</hi> were ſeverally put, and all conſum'd together by a <hi>Fire</hi> kindled underneath. But ſo much may ſerve to confirm us, that all theſe Nations after their ſettlement in the Region of <hi>Samaria,</hi> were <hi>abominable Idolaters;</hi> from the place they were now ſettled in, they took the general Name of <hi>Samaritans,</hi> by which they were known in the ſtories of ſucceeding Times.</p>
            <p>Theſe, the next Neighbours, liv'd in continual Enmity with the <hi>Jews,</hi> pretending indeed <hi>Relation</hi> and <hi>Friendſhip</hi> to them when in <hi>proſperity,</hi> but expreſſing the greateſt <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred</hi> to them when <hi>misfortunes</hi> fell upon them,<note place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. lib. 9. c. 14.</note> as <hi>Joſephus</hi> informs us. On whoſe ſide the quarrel began may be dubious; but it was grown to a great height in our Saviours time, when the Woman wonder'd at our Saviours <hi>asking water of her,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 4.9.</note> 
               <hi>ſince the Jews had then no dealing with the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95396:7"/>Samaritans.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves derive it from this very time to which the Text relates, and it may be that very oppoſition which they made to the building of the Temple, might be the Cauſe of it; for they tell us, that <hi>When</hi> Eſdras <hi>and</hi> Nehemias <hi>had aſſembled the People in Gods Temple, and had convocated</hi> 300 <hi>Prieſts, who brought with them</hi> 300 <hi>Trumpets, and as many Copies of the Law, the Levites ſounding out aloud the fatal form, they curſed the</hi> Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans <hi>with every kind of Excommunication, by the ſecret and ineffable name of God, by the Law of the two Tables, and by the Excommunication of the upper and lower Courts of Judgment</hi> (i. e. <hi>the Curſe of God and Man;</hi>) <hi>ſo that no</hi> Iſraelite <hi>ſhould dare to eat Bread with a</hi> Samaritan, <hi>it being a Crime unpardonable as eating Swines fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Druſ. de 3. Sectis lib. 3. c. 11.</note> 
               <hi>no</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan <hi>ſhould be admitted to Proſelytiſm in their Church, nor have any part in the Reſurrection of the dead;</hi> if this were true, it was no wonder there ſhould ever be a <hi>mortal Enmity</hi> and an <hi>irreconcileable feud</hi> between them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt note the <hi>forwardneſs</hi> of theſe People to aſſiſt in building the Temple of God, to joyn with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared People of God in that great Work; the <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were ſcarcely more early or forward than they, ſo <hi>ſoon as they once heard that the Children of the Captivity builded the Temple unto the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael,<note place="margin">Ver. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>they came to</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>and the chief of the Fathers, and ſaid unto them, Let us build with you;</hi> and queſtionleſs this might appear to ſome a great Evidence of devout minds. Nothing could ſeem more reaſonable, than that the Houſe where Gods Honour dwelt ſhould be rais'd apace, no help ſure could come amiſs to haſten that; And how much more <hi>ſuitable undertakers</hi> of ſuch a work, might that People be, who had liv'd in peace in their Country for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, and ſo were likely to abound in all things, than a Company of <hi>poor Exiles,</hi> driven many years ſince from their Native Land by a <hi>victorious Tyrant,</hi> and who now when they return'd home, had no <hi>Fields to reap,</hi> no <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to receive,</hi> no <hi>Houſes to hide their heads in,</hi> but lay open and defenceleſs to all the Storms and Tempeſts that might be expected from the Rage and Malice of their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Neighbours.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:95396:8"/>This <hi>offer</hi> of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> looks yet more <hi>generous</hi> in that it ſeems to tend more to the Honour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> than their own, the <hi>Temple</hi> being to be built at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and likely to add much of ſplendor to that City when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>built, but ſit only to give themſelves many tedious Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys to come up thither to worſhip; ſo that the whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign had at firſt view no appearance but of <hi>Religion for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions ſake,</hi> an eager and a pious forwardneſs to dedicate ſomewhat of that Abundance he had bleſt them with to the Honour and Service of God; And yet further they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed very <hi>Regularly</hi> in their Motion, they court not the <hi>Mobile,</hi> the <hi>poor unthinking Vulgar,</hi> who perhaps might eaſily have been impos'd upon, they looking more at gaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy outſides than at inward Sincerity; this would have lookt like unfair dealing, as if they had deſign'd to put a ſlur upon the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Chiefs by raiſing a faction againſt them, but they <hi>very fairly</hi> make their application to <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> their Leader, and the Chief of their Fathers, and there make their Offers, and ſuch as very probably in a time of need would have been accepted. Which Offers of theirs looks yet better, if we conſider,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their <hi>Plea for admittance</hi> to this work, <hi>For we ſeek your God as ye do, and we do ſacrifice unto him ſince the days of</hi> Eſar Haddon <hi>King of</hi> Aſſur,<note place="margin">V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.</note> 
               <hi>who brought us up hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> Unity in Religion certainly recommends Men to one another above all other Relations whatſoever, and what could bring more comfort to a Company of poor reſtor'd Exiles, than to meet with Neighbours <hi>worſhipping the ſame God, offering the ſame Sacrifices,</hi> and <hi>inſtructed in the ſame Divinity with themſelves,</hi> tendring withal their <hi>friendly Aſſiſtance</hi> to carry on the moſt weighty and moſt Religious Work? And it may be further obſerv'd this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of theirs was not altogether falſe.</p>
            <p>For, though we are told of the ſeveral Idols theſe People had made to themſelves, yet in the ſame Chapter we find, <hi>That in the beginning of their dwelling there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 17.25.</note> 
               <hi>they fear'd not the Lord; therefore the Lord ſent Lions among them, which ſlew ſome of them,</hi> the reaſon of which being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to be <hi>becauſe they knew not the manner of the God of the Land,</hi> the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> at their requeſt <hi>ſent them one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95396:8"/>of the Prieſts</hi> that had been brought from thence, who came to them accordingly <hi>and dwelt in</hi> Bethel, <hi>and taught them how they ſhould fear the Lord;</hi> and it follows,<note place="margin">Ver. 32, 33, 41.</note> 
               <hi>So they feared the Lord God of Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiph. adv. Haer. l. 1. p. 22.</note> Of which <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> gives us a larger account, very remarkable, but full of miſerable <hi>Anachroniſmes,</hi> of which <hi>Scaliger</hi> takes ſome notice:<note place="margin">Scal. Animad. in Euſeb. Chron. p. 74.</note> Thus <hi>Gods Judgments</hi> made them learn ſomething of <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and by the proceſs of the Story we may conclude, that upon this account, of the fearing him, God remov'd that Judgment of the Lyons from them.</p>
            <p>But their <hi>Plea</hi> was nevertheleſs <hi>deceitful,</hi> they name what was good in themſelves, but take no notice of the Crimes the Text Charges them with,<note place="margin">Ver. 33, 41.</note> 
               <hi>That in the ſervice of God, they made themſelves Prieſts of the High Places of the Lowest of the People, which ſacrificed for them in the Houſes of the High places,</hi> which was one of <hi>Jerobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ams great ſins, and for which Wrath came upon</hi> Iſrael;<note place="margin">1 Kings 13.33, 34.</note> they take no notice, that as they feared the Lord, ſo <hi>they ſerved their own Gods, their Graven Images, their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and their Childrens Children unto this day.</hi> A Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage doubtleſs added after the Return of the Jews from their Captivity. Thus their <hi>Religion</hi> was of a <hi>Mongrel kind</hi> (however it might be refin'd afterwards) part Jewiſh, part Heatheniſh, and conſequently of no real Value.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews,</hi> out of that inveterate Hatred they have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe <hi>Samaritans,</hi> load them ſtill with all the Crimes imaginable, and their <hi>Prieſthood</hi> with all the Contempt poſſible, but not altogether truly, they were as <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls them, <hi>Aemulatores Legis Judaeae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſebii Chro. p. 26.</note> 
               <hi>Imitators of the Jewiſh Model;</hi> that little Inſtruction they had from their ſingle Prieſt brought them to entertain the <hi>Books of Moſes,</hi> of which indeed they were more <hi>exact and faithful Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Voſs. Iſ. de 70 Interpr. c. 29.</note> both as to Words and Letters, than the Jews them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were. Out of Envy for this, the Jews brand them for <hi>Calf-worſhippers;</hi> to clear them from which, I muſt put in my own Conjecture concerning a Paſſage of the <hi>Nubian Geographer,</hi> obſerv'd by <hi>Scaliger</hi> and <hi>Selden:</hi> The <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher</hi> tells us, That, <hi>among many others, there is one Iſle in the Red Sea called</hi> Samerei, <hi>inhabited by Samaritans, deſcended from</hi> Sameri <hi>the Framer of the Golden Calf in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95396:9"/>the time of</hi> Moſes,<note place="margin">Selden Synt. 1. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>on whom be Peace, Scaliger</hi> tranſlates it, <hi>It is inhabited by Samaritans, the Aſſociates of the Calf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip in the time of Moſes,</hi> &amp;c. About which Paſſage whilſt they diſpute, the <hi>Geographers</hi> Miſtake is not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>Samaria</hi> was ſo call'd from <hi>Shemer,</hi> of whom <hi>Omri King of Iſrael</hi> bought the Hill upon which <hi>Samaria,</hi> as he call'd it,<note place="margin">1 Kings 16.24.</note> was built; and this was <hi>that Sameri</hi> nam'd as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by a <hi>vaſt Anachroniſm</hi> of which this ſeems to have been the Occaſion.</p>
            <p>The Jews reported the <hi>Samaritans</hi> for <hi>Calf-Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi> they ground their Report upon that Prieſts ſettling himſelf at <hi>Bethel,</hi> who firſt inſtructed them, Where <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> had ſet up <hi>a Golden Calf</hi> for Worſhip, as a <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of the True God,</hi> one of whoſe Worſhippers this Prieſt had formerly been. <hi>Jeroboams Calf</hi> unqueſtionably took its Original from that made by <hi>Aaron in the time of Moſes,</hi> which former <hi>Calf</hi> being the more notorious, the <hi>Geographer</hi> jumbles the two Stories together, and to make <hi>the Samaritans Calf-Worſhippers</hi> ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, being ignorant of the Latter, reduces them to the Ages of <hi>Moſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Conjecture I am the more ſatisfied with from that Tradition I meet with in the <hi>Itinerary of Rabbi Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> the Jew,<note place="margin">Nubien. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lor. ann. 1151. Tudelenſis mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ann. 1173. Ferrarius.</note> who was contemporary with the <hi>Nubian Geographer,</hi> and which being the common boaſt of the then ſurviving <hi>Cuthaeans</hi> or <hi>Samaritans,</hi> it might be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly known to both. <hi>Rabbi Benj.</hi> giving the Site of <hi>Neapolis,</hi> anciently call'd <hi>Sichem,</hi> adds this; <hi>There live about</hi> 100 <hi>Cuthaeans Obſervers only of the Law of Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rabbi Benj. Tud. Itin.</note> 
               <hi>the ſame whom they call Samaritans; they have Prieſts of the ſtock of Aaron the Prieſt, who reſts in Peace: and theſe they call by a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Name Aaronaeans, who marry not among the reſt of the Samaritans, but with thoſe of the ſame Sacerdotal Line, to prevent confounding their own with the Common Race yet they are the Prieſts of their Law, and prepare Victims and offer Burnt-offerings in their Congregation, and that upon the Mountain Gerizim.</hi> This Pretence of theirs to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95396:9"/>
               <hi>Stock of Aaron,</hi> might eaſily lead the <hi>Nubian</hi> into that Error. And here we may obſerve, that though our <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> afterwards adds many things to the diſgrace of theſe Samaritans, and thoſe ſpiteful enough, yet he makes no mention of any <hi>Calf</hi> then, or formerly worſhipp'd by them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We may take notice of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> given to theſe Samaritans by the <hi>Jewiſh Rulers, Zerubbabel and the reſt of the Chief of the Fathers of Iſrael ſaid unto them, You have nothing to do with us to build an Houſe unto our God, but we our ſelves together will build unto the Lord God of Iſrael, as King Cyrus the King of Perſia hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us.</hi> The Chiefs knew very well the Fallacy of that Aſſertion of theirs, they knew they fear'd the God of Iſrael, but not as themſelves did. The Jews were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded not to intermingle themſelves with any of their Neighbours for fear of Idolatry, much more were they to avoid complying in Worſhip. They had the Form of theirs preſcribed by God himſelf, which could no way admit of thoſe Errors the Prieſts of an Idolatrous Kingdom had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced. The Samaritans might fear the ſame God and offer Sacrifices to him, but ſo long as they did it not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Order preſcribed,</hi> and follow'd by the whole Jewiſh Nation as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> in one <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Body,</hi> ſo long they were not to be receiv'd as <hi>Partuers</hi> in ſo Sacred a Work, as the Building Gods Temple was. For if <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marrying</hi> with Idolaters was of dangerous Conſequence,<note place="margin">Deut. 7.3, 4 5, 6. Deut. 12.29, 30. Exod. 34.12. — 16.</note> no doubt but <hi>Communion</hi> with them in the moſt <hi>ſolemn parts</hi> of Divine Worſhip, which was the thing the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans aim'd at, would be much more pernicious; ſo that in rejecting this offer of theirs, they exactly follow'd Gods Law, and withal expreſt a punctual and due <hi>Submiſſion</hi> to the <hi>Decree</hi> of their then <hi>Lawful Prince.</hi> We are to build it together, ſay they, <hi>according to the Command of Cyrus King of Perſia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 3.</note> You have no Commiſſion to joyn with us; the Predeceſſors of the Samaritans had no Hand in raiſing the former Temple, they were not of the Seed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and therefore had no right to build a Temple to the God of <hi>Iſrael; Cyrus</hi> had choſen theſe Exiles to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what God had commanded,<note place="margin">Ezr. 1.3, 4</note> and it became not thoſe who were <hi>Subjects</hi> to the ſame Prince to Croſs his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95396:10"/>or to <hi>ſtretch</hi> his <hi>Commands</hi> beyond their <hi>firſt Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was then acknowledged by the Jews to be their own <hi>proper Work,</hi> and they had the Prophets of God to excite them to <hi>diligence</hi> in that Work,<note place="margin">Ezr. 6.14.</note> and they were to build together <hi>united</hi> among themſelves, <hi>with one Heart, and with one Mind,</hi> if they reſolv'd to admit of no Fellow <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers,</hi> their own whole Strength was but little e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to perform ſo vaſt a Work; a few of the other Tribes had joyn'd themſelves with thoſe of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin, ſuch as ſet their Hearts to ſeek the Lord God of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 11.13, — 16.</note> and thoſe were but few, the whole remnant of the twelve Tribes, but inconſiderable, to what they had been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and their Enemies ready to take all Advantages againſt them: Upon which account, as alſo to ſhew their <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> to that <hi>Prince</hi> who had reſtor'd them to their Native Country, and their <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Glory of that God,</hi> who as he had puniſh'd them for their Sins, ſo had told them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by his Prophets of this <hi>Happy Change</hi> upon their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere <hi>Repentance,</hi> it was incumbent upon them altogether, as one Man, to begin and to carry on this Work of God, and ſo the <hi>Adverſaries</hi> themſelves might be convinced, That the Temple of the True God might be built accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Command, without their Help.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the Text we are to obſerve the <hi>Behaviour</hi> of the Samaritans upon the Anſwer given them, <hi>They weakned the Hands of the People of Judah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>they troubled them in building, and hired Councellors againſt them.</hi> They weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their Hands by endeavouring to create <hi>Jealouſies and Suſpicions</hi> one of another among them, they were newly recovered out of a Miſerable Captivity, and the preſent <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penneſs and Defenceleſneſs</hi> of their Condition made every <hi>Idle Rumour</hi> terrible to them. One while they try to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trap the Governour;<note place="margin">Neh. 6.2.</note> then they charge the Jews with a <hi>Deſign of Rebellion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 6.10.</note> and hire Prophets to diſcourage the People in the Work; but, as the laſt Effect of their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, they write their <hi>Letter</hi> to the <hi>Perſian King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fur. 4.9.21, 23.</note> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him of the danger of the Jews fortifying themſelves, and ſo procure a Stop to be put to their further Procedure; Where obſerve further the <hi>Policy</hi> of theſe Adverſaries of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95396:10"/>
               <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> They ow'd <hi>Revenge</hi> to the Jews for refuſing their Help to build the Temple, the Building of which they reſolve to Hinder. But in their Letter to <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> they take no notice of that, leſt perhaps, <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his <hi>late Decree</hi> being found, their Deſign ſhould have been defeated; but they complain of former <hi>Rebellions,</hi> and they fear they would be renew'd, if the Jews had leave to build their City Walls, and here the Perſian Records might pinch them. And by this Art they gain'd their End, they having a General Command,<note place="margin">Ezr. 4.21, 22.</note> 
               <hi>to ſee that no Damage might grow to the King;</hi> took it in the largeſt ſenſe, and caus'd the building of the Temple as well as the re-edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their City to ceaſe, and thus the <hi>Poor Builders,</hi> who had ſo lately felt the Smart of a ſevere <hi>Captivity,</hi> were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of oppoſing their Malicious Neighbours, leſt an <hi>Ill Interpretation</hi> ſhould have been made of it.</p>
            <p>To make their Malice the more Effectual, they <hi>hired Councellors againſt the Jews,</hi> ſuch ſubtile Perſons who knew all the <hi>Tricks and Quirks of Law,</hi> and ſo could fright the poor Jews into a Belief that they incurr'd <hi>great Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> when indeed they had <hi>broken no Laws,</hi> and theſe could point to the Jews Enemies the moſt certain and ſecure ways of taking Advantage againſt this poor <hi>Helpleſs People;</hi> or the <hi>Councellors</hi> they hired might be ſuch <hi>great Perſons as attended the King of Perſia,</hi> whom they, as a <hi>wealthy</hi> ſort of People, <hi>Brib'd</hi> largely to aſſiſt them with their <hi>Intereſt at Court,</hi> while the Jews, who had no Stock to carry on ſuch Deſigns, went by the worſt, And to this we in ſome meaſure may attribute the Succeſs of the <hi>Letter to Artaxerxes,</hi> for had the Jews retain'd a <hi>Friend at Court,</hi> who could have put the King in mind of his <hi>Father Decree</hi> in Favour of them and the reaſon of that Decree, that it was in Obedience to the <hi>Commands of the Moſt High God,</hi> 'tis very probable the <hi>Penners</hi> of that <hi>Miſchievous Epistle</hi> had loſt their labours. And ſo much may ſerve for Explication of the Text.</p>
            <p>The Text being thus explain'd, the Obſervations I ſhall reduce from it, are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That every Deliverance from great and general Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities ought to be celebrated with a Reſtauration of Gods</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:95396:11"/>
               <hi>Publick, Ancient, and Solemn Worſhip.</hi> There can be no end put to Publick Calamities but by the Hand of God; we may ſeek for remedies elſewhere, but to no purpoſe, to him therefore the firſt of our Praiſes ought to be return'd. It was here the <hi>Jews</hi> work; no ſooner were they reſettled in the Land of their Fathers, but they apply themſelves to build again the <hi>Temple of God</hi> that had been formerly burnt; and when they afterwards neglected that pious Work, God by his Prophet checks them ſeverely: <hi>Is it time for you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gg 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Oye, to dwell in ceiled houſes, and this Houſe lie waſte? Now therefore thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Conſider your ways, ye have ſown much and bring in little; ye ear, but ye have not enough; ye drink, but ye are not fill'd with drink; ye cloath you, but there is none warm, and he that earneth wages, earneth wages to put it into a Bag with holes. Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, Conſider your ways, Go up to the Mountain, and bring Wood and build the Houſe, and I will take pleaſure in it, and I will be glorified, ſaith the Lord.</hi> That whole Book indeed is nothing but a reproof for N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>glect, a command to Induſtry, and a promiſe of Bleſſings upon their Care and Induſtry in building the Temple of God. The Author of thoſe <hi>Golden Verſes,</hi> commonly aſcrib'd to <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> adviſes well, <hi>To honour and adore the Gods in the firſt place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Pythag. Aurea Carm. Carm. 1.</note> for all other lawful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings can proſper only when that foundation is laid. This was well appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Rome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>monias omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>que <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> immortalium docuit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Populum redegit, ut quod vi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> injuriâ occupaverat impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> atque Juſtitia guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>or. in Numa.</hi>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> multitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeculis rudem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deorum m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tum injicien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſt. <hi>Liv. l. 1.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> It was not the valour and conduct of <hi>Romulus,</hi> nor the ſturdineſs of a few rough and ill-tutor'd <hi>Shepherds</hi> that could ſecure an <hi>Infant State;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he firſt inrroduced <hi>Religion</hi> among them, taught them to <hi>worſhip the Gods,</hi> and gave them a <hi>ſtated Form and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod</hi> for the performance of all <hi>Divine Offices;</hi> and it was a Remark<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble Cuſtom among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that when they ſet down to beſiege any City, they firſt tryed to anone the ſuppos'd <hi>Tutelar Deity</hi> of the place, endeavouring, with many <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> to call him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95396:11"/>out of the beleagued places, with promiſes of better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment among themſelves; ſo neceſſary did they conclude <hi>Heavens Bleſſing</hi> to make all their deſigns <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Macrob. Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. l. 3. c. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But if in the firſt beginning of affairs this <hi>Religion</hi> be ſo neceſſary, <hi>Devotion in Extremities</hi> is ſo too, and much more <hi>thankfulneſs for Deliverances.</hi> The ſame <hi>Romans,</hi> when <hi>Hannibal</hi> approacht their Gates, us'd means extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary to reconcile their falſe Gods to them,<note place="margin">Undique Matronae in publicum effuſae circa D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um delubra diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urrunt, Crini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus paſſis aras verrentes n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>bus ſupinas manus ad c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>um tenden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranteſque ut Urb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m <hi>Roman</hi> è manibus Hoſtitum eriperent, matreſque <hi>Romanas</hi> &amp; liberos parvos inviolatos ſervarent. <hi>Liv. l. 36.</hi>
               </note> that they might diveſt that terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>my, and in the time of <hi>War,</hi> though all things were yet in ſuſpence, <hi>the whole Senate, at the Generals re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, repair'd to their Temples to ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate Heaven for a Victory,</hi> and always in gratitude conſecrated ſome of the <hi>Spoils</hi> gotten in the <hi>Field</hi> to their Gods;<note place="margin">Roſm. Ant. Rom. l. 10 c 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor was this the practice only of <hi>Heathens,</hi> though by their <hi>Actions</hi> we may learn what Nature teaches; but Almighty God himſelf preſcribes it to his own People by his Prophet. And afterwards, <hi>Blow the Trumpet in</hi> Zion, <hi>ſanctifie a Faſt, call a ſolemn Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly, gather the People, ſanctifie the Congregation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel c. 1.</note> 
               <hi>aſſemble the Elders, gather the Children and thoſe that ſuck the Breaſts; let the Bridegroom go forth of his Chamber, and the Bride of her Cloſet; Let the Prieſts the Miniſters of the Lord weep between the Porch and the Altar, and let them ſay, Spare thy People, O Lord, and give not thine Heritage to reproach,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel 2.15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.17.</note> 
               <hi>that the Heathen ſhould rule over them; wherefore ſhould they ſay among the People, where is their God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>extraordinary earneſtneſs</hi> of the <hi>Devotions</hi> of thoſe that are in <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> is a ſtrong evidence of that <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary gratitude</hi> due to that <hi>God,</hi> who on ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hears and anſwers our Prayers; and he that minds but what <hi>Vows</hi> Calamitous perſons always make on condition of Heavens aſſiſtance, may learn from thence, that <hi>Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for deliverances receiv'd,</hi> is a <hi>principle Originally</hi> ſo ſixt in the Heart of Man, that the moſt <hi>careleſs</hi> and <hi>ſtupid</hi> of Mankind know not how to elude it. 'Tis certain, that <hi>coldneſs</hi> in the exerciſe of <hi>Religion</hi> is the <hi>grand Excitative
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95396:12"/>of Divine Anger,</hi> the <hi>ultimate cauſe</hi> of thoſe Puniſhments which the hand of God inflicts upon us; for though <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, Drunkenneſs, Whoring, Covetouſneſs, Theft, Murder, Malice, Treachery, Diſobedience, Rebellion,</hi> and the like, are all <hi>Crying Sins,</hi> and of themſelves <hi>merit Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance,</hi> yet they are always accompany'd with ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable defect, in the <hi>outward Solemnities of Religion:</hi> ſo that let <hi>men ſuffer</hi> by us what way ſoever, <hi>God</hi> will be ſure to have a ſhare in the <hi>diſhonour.</hi> An <hi>Hypocrite</hi> I know may go far, but one way or other, even in outward per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances he muſt fail; for thoſe <hi>Scruples,</hi> that nicety he muſt neceſſarily pretend to for the Credit of that he calls his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and to perſwade Men of his exactneſs in Religious matters, thoſe very <hi>Scruples</hi> will betray him into that <hi>Sin of diſhonouring God in his Publick Worſhip;</hi> for in that he will either not be <hi>conſtant,</hi> or not <hi>early,</hi> or not be have himſelf <hi>reverently</hi> or <hi>devoutly</hi> in it; or not <hi>Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly,</hi> according to what is preſcrib'd by <hi>Lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> in the Church; or he will evidence and avow his greater reſpect to ſome peculiar <hi>Fancies</hi> and <hi>Enthuſiaſms</hi> of his own, than to what is <hi>preſcrib'd.</hi> Every one of which 'tis impoſſible for the <hi>ſubtileſt Hypocrite</hi> to avoid, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of which is look't upon with another Eye by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, than ordinarily it is by us: And all, or any of theſe, as adding <hi>perfection</hi> to Sin, at the ſame time <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate</hi> Gods diſpleaſure, and bring down the heavieſt of his Judgments upon Men.</p>
            <p>But where <hi>Vice</hi> in General overflows a <hi>Nation</hi> or <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> there <hi>Gods Worſhip</hi> muſt as generally be diſreſpected, all <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> in it be deſtroy'd. He that is unjuſt to Man will be unjuſt to God.<note place="margin">1 John 4.20.</note> S. <hi>John</hi>'s Argument holds good here, <hi>He that loves not his Brother whom he has ſeen, how ſhall he love God whom he hath not ſeen;</hi> and where that <hi>lurking Vice</hi> reſides that puts on <hi>Scrupulous Religion</hi> for a <hi>Cloak,</hi> there above all, that <hi>Beauty, Decency</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> that ought to be in <hi>Gods Service</hi> is contemn'd and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and <hi>his Houſe</hi> eſteem'd no more than the <hi>Commoneſt</hi> or the <hi>vileſt Place.</hi> This Truth the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees</hi> in our <hi>Saviours</hi> times give <hi>teſtimony</hi> to; none cry'd out louder of <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95396:12"/>Lord,</hi> and none abus'd that Temple more; they profan'd it ſo far as to make the meek <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſeverely to tell them, <hi>My Houſe ſhould be call'd the Houſe of Prayer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 21.13.</note> 
               <hi>but ye have made it a Den of Thieves.</hi> In ſuch caſes, if God be angry who can wonder? If God confound that People who labour to <hi>cloud his Glory,</hi> and to render his <hi>Service ſordid</hi> and <hi>nauſeous,</hi> he muſt then be juſtified when he ſpeaks, though in anger, and clear when he is judged.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>Solemn Worſhip of God,</hi> the <hi>Contempt</hi> of which has ſuch dreadful effects, ought firſt to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded when the Almighty ſheaths his Sword again, and reſtores <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Proſperity</hi> to a People. So ſoon as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were freed from the <hi>Aegyptian Bondage,</hi> and but yet on their way to the <hi>Promis'd Land,</hi> they were call'd upon by God himſelf to build a <hi>Tabernacle</hi> and <hi>Ark</hi> with all their Furniture, before which they might offer their <hi>daily Sacrifices. David,</hi> when he fled from <hi>Abſolom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 25.</note> was careful leſt <hi>this Ark</hi> ſhould ſuffer by being carry'd with him in his <hi>flight; Carry it back,</hi> ſays he, <hi>into the City, if I ſhall find favour in the ſight of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.25.</note> 
               <hi>he will bring me again, and ſhew me both it and his habitation.</hi> When he return'd indeed, he preſently was for raiſing a Temple to the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> his Redeemer; and ſince God permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him not to build it, he provided Treaſure for his Son to build it with; He preſcrib'd the method of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,<note place="margin">1 Chron. Chapters 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27, &amp;c.</note> and fixt Orders for its exact performance in that Temple. As for the Temple it ſelf, where this coſt was to be beſtow'd, and theſe Orders obſerv'd, <hi>David</hi> declares, <hi>The Houſe that is to be builded for the Lord must be exceeding magnifical, of fame and of glory throughout all Countries;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 22.5.</note> and the Reaſon he gives is remarkable, <hi>The work is great,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29.1.</note> 
               <hi>for the Palace is not for Man, but for the Lord God.</hi> And this care of <hi>David</hi>'s was ſo juſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffectual, that in <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi>'s time we find the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> obeying the paſt <hi>Commands of David,</hi> uſing the <hi>Inſtruments of David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 29.25, — 30.</note> and praiſing God in <hi>the Words of David;</hi> and he that ſhall but read profane Story,<note place="margin">Multa &amp; epu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta ibi Regum populorumque viſuntur munera quaeque magnificentiâ ſuâ reddentium vota gratam voluntatem &amp; Decrum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſa manifeſtant. <hi>Juſtinus</hi> de templo <hi>Delphico. Lib. 24. c. 8.</hi>
               </note> and ſee what large <hi>Donaria</hi> all Countries appropriated to their <hi>Sacred Temples,</hi> upon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95396:13"/>
               <hi>Dangers eſcap'd</hi> or <hi>Victories obtain'd,</hi> or the <hi>Sacred Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> and view the <hi>prodigious Liberalities</hi> of <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> and the Nobles of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to the Temple of God, muſt needs conclude, the Service of God was by that means render'd <hi>glorious</hi> and <hi>beautiful,</hi> the <hi>gratitude</hi> of Men to God very <hi>commendable,</hi> and that thoſe who left us thoſe great Examples were not all of them either <hi>Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> or <hi>Fools.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed Men may pretend what they will, they'l never perſwade any in their ſenſes to believe them <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> to God for removing Common Judgements, who do not repair the <hi>decays of Divine Worſhip,</hi> and endeavour to reſtore its <hi>priſtine exactneſs</hi> and <hi>ſplendor,</hi> and an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form</hi> celebration of Gods Praiſes is the beſt proof of an agreeing ſenſe of his infinite Goodneſs. And thus the Chriſtians of old in each <hi>Diſtinct</hi> reſpectively were United in the ſame <hi>Forms of Worſhip,</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church Concordant in the ſame matter,</hi> and the whole World con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the <hi>Beauty and Harmony of that Religion,</hi> whoſe Profeſſors addreſt themſelves to God, ſo <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitedly</hi> for Matter, and with ſo <hi>little diſparity</hi> in <hi>Words and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods,</hi> even that diſparity confirming the <hi>truth of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,</hi> the greatneſs of the true God, and the Divinity of the Man Chriſt Jeſus, whom, <hi>though Crucified,</hi> the Chriſtian World with the greateſt <hi>fervour</hi> and <hi>devotion</hi> ador'd and invocated.</p>
            <p>'Tis eaſie to Object, That though great <hi>thankfulneſs</hi> is really due to God after <hi>great Deliverances,</hi> yet 'tis <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in what place, by what perſon, in what order</hi> Gods praiſe in his Worſhip is declar'd. 'Tis true, a Man may be heard with <hi>Job</hi> from a <hi>Dunghil,</hi> with <hi>Jonah</hi> from the <hi>Oceans bottom,</hi> with <hi>Jeremiah</hi> from the <hi>miry Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon,</hi> or with <hi>Daniel</hi> from the <hi>Lions Den;</hi> but ſcarce any wiſe Man would chuſe thoſe places for his <hi>Devotions,</hi> if he were at <hi>Liberty:</hi> And my <hi>Groom</hi> or <hi>Scullion</hi> may be heard in their Prayers as ſoon as I; but it would ſhew little reſpect to Gods Service, ſhould I call them to officiate in the Head of my Family in a <hi>Scullery</hi> or <hi>Stable,</hi> with their <hi>Horſe</hi> or <hi>Kitchen Habiliments</hi> about them. <hi>Days of deliverance</hi> are days of <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Feaſting,</hi> and the <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95396:13"/>of Gladneſs</hi> ought then to be worn, and our <hi>grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> to put on the <hi>faireſt face</hi> of <hi>Order, Lovelineſs</hi> and <hi>Beauty;</hi> thoſe <hi>Sins</hi> for which we ſuffer ſhould be <hi>forſaken,</hi> our <hi>thankful Reſentments</hi> of <hi>Gods Goodneſs</hi> ſhould be expos'd to the Worlds view, and that ſo, that <hi>Religion</hi> for its <hi>deformity</hi> may not be made a <hi>Scar-crow,</hi> nor <hi>Slovenli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> the meaſure of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> nor <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> the <hi>Eſſence of Devotion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the practice of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> in the Text we may Obſerve,<note place="margin">Obſerv. 2.</note> 
               <hi>That the Enemies of Religion always ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to hinder the Restauration of Gods Solemn and Publick Worſhip.</hi> The Charms of pure and undefil'd Religion, and the Worſhip attending it, are terrible and odious to the Prince of Darkneſs, he renders it a <hi>Mormo</hi> or <hi>Bugbear</hi> to his wretched Slaves, and cannot endure its allurements ſhould reach the Souls of <hi>thinking perſons;</hi> and therefore as by his <hi>Wiles</hi> and <hi>Policies</hi> he endeavours to put a ſlur upon <hi>Piety,</hi> to render it <hi>ugly</hi> and <hi>ridiculous</hi> in the ſight of Men, that ſo it may crouch to growing Impieties: So when men formerly mad after Sin, begin to return to their almoſt <hi>loſt Wits</hi> again, he tries all ways to hinder the good Effects of <hi>Repentance,</hi> that ſo profeſt <hi>Penitents may return with the Dog to his Vomit, and with the Sow that is waſh'd to her wallowing in the mire.</hi> That Sin ſhould abound, and that Vengeance ſhould once more deluge the World is his aim, and therefore he ſtudies to obſtruct whatſoever tends to <hi>Reformation</hi> in thoſe things that are really amiſs. Whatſoever miſchief the Devil deſigns, his <hi>buſie Agents</hi> here on Earth, who think ſcorn to be <hi>damn'd alone,</hi> carry on with the greateſt vigour, and labour to engage all whom poſſibly they can pervert into the ſame Service: ſo the People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, when God had ſcourg'd them frequently for their Sins, and by his puniſhments reduced them to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> though their <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Reſolutions</hi> were never ſo many of reforming themſelves to the Pattern God had preſcrib'd them, their Reſolutions all vaniſh'd into Air, and eaſie Temptations drew them to dangerous relapſes, as we read in the Book of <hi>Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:95396:14"/>
               <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> King of <hi>Judah</hi> was eminent in <hi>wickedneſs,</hi> as his Father <hi>Hezekiah</hi> had been in <hi>piety; He did that which was evil in the ſight of the Lord, like to the Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Heathen whom the Lord had caſt out before the Children of</hi> Iſrael; <hi>nay, he made</hi> Judah <hi>and all the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>to erre worſe than the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then whom the Lord had deſtroy'd;</hi> for which God deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd him a Captive to the King of <hi>Babylon;</hi> where, when he humbled himſelf, God was entreated of him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd him to his Kingdom. This Mercy made him <hi>know that the Lord only was God;</hi> but though he endeavour'd afterwards in <hi>Gratitude</hi> to his <hi>Deliverer,</hi> to clear <hi>Gods Temple,</hi> to repair his <hi>Altar,</hi> and to reduce the <hi>Temple Service</hi> to its <hi>Ancient Glory,</hi> it was but in vain; <hi>His Son,</hi> the Heir of his Crown, the Witneſs of his Repentance and the Reaſons of it, was upon his Death too eaſily ſeduced, and inſtead of perfecting the good work begun by his Father, he only outſtript him in Sin, <hi>He ſacrificed to all the Carv'd Images which</hi> Manaſſes <hi>in his folly had made,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chron. 23.2, 9, 13, 16, 22.</note> 
               <hi>but hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled not himſelf as</hi> Manaſſes <hi>had done, but treſpaſſed more and more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we examine the Caſe of theſe <hi>return'd Exiles,</hi> we ſhall ſee, that notwithſtanding Gods and the Kings <hi>Favour</hi> to them, the <hi>excellent Examples</hi> of <hi>Zerubbabel, Jeſhua, Nehemiah,</hi> and the other <hi>Chiefs,</hi> and the Divine Excita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zechariah;</hi> notwithſtanding the <hi>forward Zeal</hi> they ſhew'd at firſt to repair the ſacred <hi>Ruins</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> they were ſo unhappy, that even ſome of their <hi>own Nobles,</hi> for whom, as well as the reſt, God had done ſuch great things, held Correſpondence with the Enemies of their Church,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hem. 5.17, 18, 19.</note> to the notorious hazard of their Religion; but when all theſe obſtacles were paſt over, when the Houſe of God was built, the <hi>Ancient forms of Worſhip</hi> were reeſtabliſh'd, and their compleat Joy outwardly expreſt by that Care, for <hi>that the Lord had made them joyful,</hi>
               <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 22.</note> 
               <hi>and turn'd the Heart of the King of</hi> Aſſyria <hi>to them, to ſtrengthen their hands in the work of the Houſe of God, the God of</hi> Iſrael. But, alas! Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs too too ſoon prevail'd again, and the prophaneſs and contempt of Gods Service, grew intolerable; on which
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95396:14"/>account God made the Kings of <hi>Syria</hi> their Scourge, that Temple, their Pride and Glory, was defil'd by their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, as it had been by themſelves, and <hi>Judas Maccabeus</hi> once more compell'd to a <hi>Reformation;</hi> but ſtill Wicked men were buſie and active. And when our Saviour came into the World to rectifie the Errors of miſtaken Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the oppoſition he found was ſo ſtrong as ſeem'd, and was indeed to Humane powers irremediable. And Laſtly, Let us view thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Rules</hi> preſcrib'd by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves, for the ſettling <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in the Church of Chriſt, and we ſhall ſee ſo many <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Hereſies</hi> rais'd by the Devil and wicked Men to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and diſannul them, that nothing leſs than an Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent Power could have preſerv'd them to this day.</p>
            <p>And yet that <hi>due</hi> and <hi>regular Veneration</hi> of the Divine Majeſty, is ſo naturally fixt in the minds of Men, that the moſt reſolv'd Enemies of Goodneſs are frequently balkt themſelves, and downright <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to <hi>Publick, Solemn</hi> and <hi>Decent Worſhip,</hi> oft-times diſguſts both themſelves and others; Hell, in this caſe, drives them to the other Extream, and makes them <hi>overdo</hi> what God and the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of his Publick Worſhip require, as if there could be no Mean between the <hi>ſluttery and naſtineſs</hi> of a <hi>Common proſtitute</hi> and the <hi>gariſh Extravagance of a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Harlot.</hi> And thus did Ill Men prevail formerly upon the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, and taught them by this means to <hi>preach for Doctrines the Commandments of Men;</hi> and thus the Chriſtian Worſhip in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was perverted, where ſo many things, not only <hi>unneceſſary</hi> but <hi>inconvenient,</hi> not only <hi>ſuperfluous</hi> but <hi>ridiculous,</hi> have been introduc'd, that <hi>Paganiſm</hi> in its greateſt Wild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs could not outvy them; and by this means the very Subſtance of true Sacred Worſhip has been expos'd to contempt, and ſome have been ſo far bewitcht with an <hi>empty ſhew,</hi> as to reſt in that without examining the <hi>real weight</hi> of things.</p>
            <p>Theſe have been the ſad Effects of that <hi>Oppoſition</hi> which the <hi>Enemies of Piety</hi> have made to the <hi>reſettling Gods Worſhip</hi> in a <hi>Publick ſolemn Way;</hi> and that they ſhould not always ſtudy for and effect thus much, there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95396:15"/>can be no reaſon given but from the infinite <hi>Diviſions</hi> among theſe very Adverſaries themſelves, from whence 'tis hop'd that, according to our Saviours expreſſion, <hi>the Kingdom of Satan divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 12.26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, were Piety once totally baniſh'd the World, thoſe <hi>inteſtine Feuds</hi> among the Slaves of Hell would ſoon grow <hi>irreconcileable;</hi> Sin would make them, like thoſe who ſprung from the <hi>Dragons Teeth</hi> ſown by <hi>Cad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> to draw their Swords in an immmediate War, till they had ruin'd one another. But alas! the Caſe is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo happy here, while God has any Servants, though their <hi>Quarrels</hi> are never ſo great among themſelves, they <hi>unite</hi> but too too cloſe in <hi>perſecuting</hi> and <hi>afflicting</hi> them: So theſe <hi>Samaritans,</hi> though of ſo many <hi>different Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> and engag'd in ſuch <hi>diſagreeing Idolatries,</hi> yet could all joyn to hinder the building the Temple of the true God; for though wicked Men of all kinds are at ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great a diſtance among themſelves, yet <hi>Truth</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing equally an <hi>Enemy</hi> to them all, it moves their <hi>Hatred</hi> ſo much againſt it ſelf, that other Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>guſts and Broyls are ſoon forgotten:<note place="margin">Matth. 16.1. Ch. 22.16.</note> So the <hi>Phariſees, Sadduces,</hi> and <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> labour'd at all times to <hi>undermine each other,</hi> but readily combin'd together <hi>to deſtroy our Saviour.</hi> The more vigorous and bright Truth's Luſtre is, the more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent will the aſſaults of its Oppoſers be: So it prov'd in the Primitive Church, many and abſurd <hi>Haereſies</hi> ſprung up in it, the Breaches between the different <hi>Hereticks</hi> were <hi>irreparable,</hi> and yet they liv'd almoſt in a conſtant <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> againſt the <hi>true Catholick Church of Chriſt,</hi> and he that examines <hi>Church Hiſtory</hi> will find, that when Peace gave the greateſt Ornaments to Chriſtianity, the <hi>Muſhroom Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> grew up the faſteſt; as on the contrary, when <hi>Religion</hi> grew <hi>indifferent,</hi> and the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of it <hi>Luke-warm, Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> ſeem'd to lay down their Weapons, as if <hi>Hell</hi> had then no more employment for them.</p>
            <p>But when thoſe who ador'd the true God, to maintain his Honour, judg'd no <hi>Coſt</hi> too great to adorn his Temples, and the Devil found it impoſſible to eradicate that <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> out of Mens minds which taught them to do ſo; he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95396:15"/>try'd another way, and reſolv'd himſelf not to be inferior to his <hi>Soveraign,</hi> no <hi>Temples</hi> ſhould be rais'd more <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent,</hi> no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils more coſtly,</hi> no <hi>Sacrifices more expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi> to the <hi>Supream Deity</hi> than thoſe he aſſum'd to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and the worſt of Men, in this reſpect, ſeem'd aemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of their Bounty who expended moſt for the <hi>Ornature</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian Oratory;</hi> a thing which obſerv'd, but not well underſtood by many, made them afraid of even a <hi>decent Beauty and Magnificence in the Houſe of God,</hi> as if approaching too near <hi>Paganiſm</hi> or <hi>Superſtition;</hi> as if becauſe ſome <hi>Heathen Tyrants</hi> had formerly aſſerted to themſelves <hi>Divine Honours,</hi> therefore now no <hi>Honour</hi> at all ought to be given to <hi>Chriſtian Kings and Princes;</hi> or as if becauſe ſome <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi> formerly had liv'd in a <hi>Royal Palace,</hi> therefore a <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> muſt ſettle his <hi>Throne</hi> no higher than a <hi>Dunghil.</hi> But he who truly <hi>loves God</hi> will <hi>reverence his Sanctuary,</hi> and he who loves a <hi>neat Service and Attendance</hi> in his <hi>own Houſe,</hi> will never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure <hi>meanneſs</hi> or <hi>ſlovenlineſs</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of God;</hi> and he who can be content to dwell himſelf in <hi>cieled Palaces,</hi> will not be willing the <hi>Ark of God</hi> ſhould remain among <hi>Curtains,</hi> whilſt the <hi>Samaritan</hi> ſtrives to overthrow it, and when once overthrown to keep it down.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the Enemies of Religion find no ſurer way of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing the grateful Reſtauration of Gods Service,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſer. 3.</note> 
               <hi>than an Hypocritical Pretence to joyn in the Work:</hi> The Devil is never ſo truly Dreadful as when he puts on the Shape of an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> otherwiſe every one ſtands upon his Guard, but then the <hi>Subtile Serpent</hi> inſinuates himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Boſoms</hi> of thoſe who leaſt ſuſpect his <hi>Poyſonous Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> And wicked Men can never poſſibly do ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, as when they put on the <hi>Viſor of Piety;</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God avoid them when they appear like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but when the <hi>Sheeps Clothing</hi> has inveſted the <hi>Wolf,</hi> even <hi>He</hi> may paſs for a very <hi>Innocent Creature:</hi> This therefore is the laſt Reſult of <hi>Helliſh Policy,</hi> That <hi>roaring Lion, who walks about continually ſeeking whom he may devour,</hi> makes uſe frequently of the <hi>Foxes, the little Foxes,</hi> to ruine Gods Church; to that end the Samaritans here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to build Gods Temple with the Jews, they declare
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95396:16"/>their <hi>Reverence to the ſame God,</hi> their <hi>offering the ſame Sacrifices,</hi> a very fair <hi>Conformity,</hi> as they pretend, and which undoubredly in a ſhort time would have purchas'd for them the Title of <hi>The Church of the Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not to be queſtion'd, but that the <hi>acknowledgment of the True God,</hi> and <hi>the offering due Sacrifices to him as God,</hi> is the main Foundation of true <hi>Religion,</hi> but a bare <hi>Foundation</hi> without a <hi>Superſtructure</hi> is of no worth, for upon theſe <hi>Principles, plainly and evidently</hi> depend a great Number of other things, which, if not obſerv'd, prove that the Foundation was never truly own'd: For if a Man believe indeed that <hi>there is a God,</hi> and by <hi>offering Sacrifices</hi> acknowledges there is a <hi>Duty</hi> owing to that <hi>God,</hi> nothing can be <hi>commanded</hi> by that God, <hi>nothing</hi> forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, but the <hi>Man,</hi> if he hopes for <hi>Salvation,</hi> muſt ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to the utmoſt of his Power <hi>obey it;</hi> in which point the <hi>Samaritans</hi> fail'd foully. St. <hi>Pauls</hi> words were true of them,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>When they knew God, they glorified him not as God, but became vain in their Imaginations, and their fooliſh Heart was darkned; they fear'd God, but wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipp'd their own graven Images:</hi> Upon account of which though it be ſaid <hi>that they fear'd the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 17.33. Ver. 34.</note> yet 'tis aſſerted again, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto this day they do after the former manners, they fear not the Lord, neither do they after their Statutes or after their Ordinances, or after the Law and Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which the Lord commanded the Children of Jacob;</hi> inferring plainly the ſame from their Practice, which I would do, that <hi>though for fear they acknowledg'd God, yet ſo long as they obey'd not the Injunctions of that God, their Profeſſion was but Falſe and Vain.</hi> And it's to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, That <hi>all the Commands</hi> of God muſt be punctually o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd;<note place="margin">Smiths diſc. p 346.</note> Men may not cull out this or another according to their own Fancies, and as the Jews themſelves have pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed ſince, the Rule being infallibly Authentick, That <hi>whoſoever ſhall keep the whole Law and yet offend in one point,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jam. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>he is guilty of All;</hi> the Reaſon is becauſe he breaks that very Foundation he builds upon, the Confeſſion of a God, and our Duty to him. The Apoſtle makes the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, For he that ſaid, Do not commit Adultery, ſaid alſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 11.</note> 
               <hi>do not Kill; now if thou commit no Adultery, yet if
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95396:16"/>thou Kill, thou art become a Tranſgreſſor of the Law:</hi> So then, <hi>if any man pretend, out of a ſenſe of his Duty to God, to do one or more things, and yet minds not ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which God has commanded as well as thoſe, his whole Obedience is nothing, and his whole pretence a Lye,</hi> he really, with the Fool, <hi>ſays in his Heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 53.1.</note> 
               <hi>there is no God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will <hi>Cavils or Excuſes</hi> be admitted here, or the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity</hi> of our Duty in any Part be a ſufficient Plea; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian is bound, as far as poſſible, to enquire into the <hi>Word of God</hi> as left written for his Inſtruction, and to do of himſelf what he finds expreſt as his Duty there: and <hi>further,</hi> I'le grant him, that where there is <hi>no Law,</hi> there can be <hi>no Tranſgreſſion;</hi> where men <hi>cannot</hi> know of any more to be done by them, they ſhall not be condemn'd for not doing more. But ſince God has appointed <hi>perſons</hi> law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call'd to <hi>ſtudy the Scriptures,</hi> and to <hi>inſtruct the People</hi> in his Church, what thoſe Perſons ſo appointed learn and deduce truly from <hi>Scripture</hi> is to be attended to; and whereas all <hi>Divine Commands</hi> have a certain <hi>Connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> one with another, ſo that there can be no <hi>claſhing</hi> or <hi>contradiction</hi> between them, though ſuch things be not <hi>in terminis</hi> commanded, yet if they be found ſo <hi>concordant</hi> to the <hi>explicit and plain Rules,</hi> ſuch things are to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally</hi> ſubmitted to and obey'd: And hence it was that ſince among <hi>the Jews the Prieſts Lips were to preſerve knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 2.7. Deut. 17.8, 13.</note> and the People were to addreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves to them for <hi>information in the more doubtful parts of their Duties;</hi> Theſe Samaritans were to have apply'd themſelves to thoſe <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and to have <hi>conform'd</hi> in all things to their <hi>Preſcriptions,</hi> if they intended really to become <hi>Partners</hi> with them in one <hi>Common Church So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 'tis <hi>Folly</hi> to believe that God gave greater <hi>Power</hi> or <hi>Priviledges</hi> in theſe Caſes to the <hi>Jewiſh,</hi> than to the <hi>Chriſtian Teachers;</hi> for whereas among the Jews, the <hi>Prince and the Prieſt</hi> were joyn'd together in the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of <hi>Gods True Religion,</hi> ſo whereſoever the <hi>Prince and People profeſs Chriſtianity,</hi> their Work is the ſame, the <hi>Prince defends,</hi> and with the <hi>Prieſt declares</hi> the true
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95396:17"/>
               <hi>Catholick Faith.</hi> And upon this account it is, that the <hi>Burthen</hi> that lyes upon the <hi>Teachers of the Church</hi> is the greater, where the <hi>Preacher</hi> delivers <hi>apparent Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods</hi> and the <hi>People</hi> are ſeduced by him, the <hi>Fault</hi> is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided between the <hi>Inſtructor and the Inſtructed,</hi> it being his work to <hi>preach the Truth ſincerely,</hi> and the <hi>Peoples</hi> to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures daily to ſee whether theſe things be ſo;</hi> but in <hi>Obſcurer</hi> caſes if the <hi>people be ſeduced,</hi> 'tis wholly their <hi>Teachers Fault,</hi> he being more <hi>knowing</hi> than they, and being bound not to teach others at random, but what he knows <hi>certainly and neceſſarily true;</hi> and for ſuch <hi>Errors,</hi> not the <hi>People, but the Preacher,</hi> ſhall be condemn'd at laſt.</p>
            <p>This <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Obedience</hi> being ſo <hi>indiſpenſibly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> to make a really Pious Man and a Good Chriſtian, and thoſe who ſubmit not to it, being conſequently <hi>no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> whatever they call themſelves, but <hi>downright Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans and Infidels;</hi> nothing can be more plain, than that ſuch can deſire an <hi>Intereſt or Concern</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> with no other Deſign but to <hi>Ruin</hi> it: 'Tis no hard matter to blind the Eyes of Men, ſo that ordinarily they may ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no harm, but 'tis not ſo eaſie for Men to forſake their <hi>own Natures,</hi> or to deſign the <hi>Conſervation</hi> of thoſe Laws they never deſign to ſubmit to. The <hi>Samaritans</hi> had they been entertain'd by the <hi>Jews,</hi> would have pry'd into their moſt <hi>retir'd privacies</hi> and <hi>intendments,</hi> Sacred or Civil, that they might ſo have <hi>counterpois'd</hi> their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and have <hi>betray'd</hi> their Deſigns to their Enemies, and others who <hi>fear the Lord, and yet follow their own baſe and lewd Imaginations,</hi> being ſo many <hi>Penſioners of Hell,</hi> i. e. aſſiſted by the Devil for their faithful Adherence to his Deſigns, ſo far as his <hi>Interest</hi> goes in <hi>this World; thoſe Perſons</hi> would by all means get <hi>admiſſion to Employment</hi> in the Church, that ſo they may Croſs the great Deſign of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndeceiving and Reforming Mankind;</hi> and by introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, abetting and encouraging <hi>Atheiſm, Profaneneſs, Schiſm and Diſobedience,</hi> under a ſhew of <hi>Zeal for Trifles,</hi> may <hi>betray</hi> it to all its moſt dangerous <hi>Enemies:</hi> So Men of <hi>Factious and Diſcontented Spirits,</hi> by eager pretences to <hi>Loyalty,</hi> labour hard to be truſted with <hi>Arms,</hi> that with
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95396:17"/>them in their Hands they may at once <hi>ingratiate</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with <hi>Rebels,</hi> and <hi>aſſiſt them.</hi> Which Miſchief, that it may be the better avoided, we muſt proceed to</p>
            <p>Obſ. 4. <hi>That the true Servants of God can never without danger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſer. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and therefore in prudence never will admit ſuch Perſons at their requeſt to joyn with them in reſtoring Gods Service and Worſhip, ſeeing their deſign must be ſo fatal to the Church it ſelf.</hi> This we learn from the <hi>wiſe behaviour</hi> of the <hi>Jewiſh Chiefs</hi> in the Text, who would not upon any account receive <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> from the <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> in <hi>building Gods Temple; You have nothing to do with us,</hi> ſay they, <hi>but we only will build together.</hi> I rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily yield, that the <hi>Governours of Gods true Church</hi> ought to make and admit as many <hi>Converts</hi> to the Truths of the Goſpel as they can, and to reduce as many <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> as may be to <hi>Catholick Communion;</hi> but to admit them further than bare <hi>Church Memberſhip,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out long tryal of their ſincerity, would be little elſe than madneſs. A <hi>Heretick,</hi> a <hi>Schiſmatick,</hi> though they <hi>profeſs Chriſtianity,</hi> are no more <hi>Chriſtians</hi> indeed than <hi>Pagans;</hi> as he is no more my Friend who engages himſelf in my acquaintance to ruine me, or who endeavours it after my acquaintance, than he who every where publiſhes himſelf my Enemy. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> determines it ſo when he tells us, <hi>He that is not with me,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Matth. 12.30</note> he that is not ſincerely and wholly on my ſide <hi>is againſt me.</hi> Now that ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are not <hi>true Chriſtians</hi> ſhould be concern'd in <hi>edifying or defending the Church of Chriſt,</hi> is extremely unreaſonable, this were to make the <hi>Wolf</hi> the Shepherd of the <hi>Sheep,</hi> and would ſoon render the Church of God <hi>ſentinam malignantium,</hi> the very Sink or Common Sewer of all the Ill the World contains, and the Scoff which <hi>Julian the Apoſtate,</hi> by the Mouth of <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> puts upon the Chriſtian Doctrine would be a real Truth, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is an Adulterer or Sodomite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Jul. Caeſ.</note> 
               <hi>whoſoever is a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, whoſoever is polluted or under the greateſt Curſe, let him come boldly; for waſht once with this Water,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95396:18"/>(meaning that of <hi>Baptiſm,</hi>) <hi>I'le preſent him inſtantly pure and clean from all his Crimes: nay, ſhould he again relapſe into his former guilty ſtate, let him but beat his Breaſt, and knock his Head, and he ſhall preſently be holy again.</hi> So eaſie would an admittance into the Church be, none could poſſibly be found ſo bad, but he would be receiv'd into one Society or another; and this would be the effect of that which ſome perſons ſeem ſo eager for, and that is <hi>Indulgence</hi> or <hi>Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Toleration,</hi> known ſometimes by the names of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Indulgence,</hi> the thing which in effect theſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> deſir'd, ſeems to have been very <hi>odious</hi> to thoſe who ſome Years ſince <hi>held the Pulpit</hi> in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Congregations, as appears by the <hi>united Votes</hi> of a conſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rable number of them; <hi>We are ſtruck with horror and aſtoniſhment,</hi> ſay they, <hi>at the endeavours of many for it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A <hi>Toleration</hi> would be putting a Sword into a mad mans hand, a Cup of Poyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n in the hand of a Child, a letting looſe of mad Men with Firebrands in their hands, an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing a City of Refuge in mens Conſciences for the Devil to fly to, a laying a ſtumbling Block before the blind, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming liberty to the Wolves to come into Chriſts Fold to prey upon his Lambs, a Toleration of Soul Murder (the greateſt Murder of all other,) and for the eſtabliſhing whereof damned Souls in Hell would accurſe men on Earth; Neither would it be to provide for tender Conſciences, but to take away all Conſcience; if Evil be ſuffered, it will not ſuffer Good; if Error be not forcibly kept under it will be Superior, which we here the rather ſpeak of to undeceive thoſe weak Ones, who under the ſpecious pretext of <hi>Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> (being indeed liberty of Error, Scandal, Schiſm, Hereſie, Diſhonouring God, Oppoſing the Truth, hindering Reformation and ſeducing Others) are charm'd by Satan into a better liking of an unconſcientious Teleration. We dread to think what horrid Blaſphemies would be belched out againſt God, what vile abominations would be committed; how the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of neareſt Relations would be violated; what differences and diviſions there would be in Families and Congregations; what heart-burnings would be cauſed; what diſobedience to the Civil Magiſtrate, that might be palliated over with a pretence of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as well as other Opinions and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices; what diſturbance of the Civil Peace and diſſolution of all Humane Society and of all Government in the Church and Commonwealth, if once liberty were given by a Law for men to profeſs and practice what Opinions they pleas'd, &amp;c. <hi>Harmonious conſent of</hi> Lancaſhire <hi>Miniſters with thoſe of</hi> London, <hi>p. 12, 13. printed 1648.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>it looks as if men could not ſin faſt enough unleſs they were bidden, as if God were not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready enough diſhonoured, except the Throne of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity were ſet up framing Miſchief by a Law; or as if men were afraid</hi> Error <hi>(a goodly Plant to be cheriſht) would not grow faſt enough except it were made much of. We have ſearched the Sacred Records, and yet we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find that ever ſuch a thing was practic'd with approbation from God, from the time of</hi> Adams <hi>Creation to the ſealing up that Sacred Volume, and the ceaſing of Viſions and all new Divine Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> And again, <hi>It would
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95396:18"/>be no part of</hi> Englands <hi>Thankfulneſs, after ſo many Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances and Mercies receiv'd from God, to grant men Liberty openly to blaſpheme him, at their pleaſure to wreſt the Scripture to their own deſtruction; to trample upon his Holy Ordinances, ſlight and contemn all Miniſtry, deſpiſe his Meſſengers, commit all manner of abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and for every one to go a whoring after their own Inventions,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Harm. conſ. p. 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>which yet would be the Effects of a lawleſs Toleration.</hi> This was ſubſcrib'd by the Miniſters of a whole County. If then it be (as they truly aſſert) a thing ſo extreamly ill to <hi>indulge</hi> perſons of <hi>different Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions</hi> at all; much more is it ſo, to let them be engaged in the <hi>greateſt and nobleſt work</hi> the Church of Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes. <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> are Crimes of ſo <hi>bewitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> a Nature, as we find by Experience, that thoſe <hi>Lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of either kind, who happen to <hi>renounce</hi> their Errors, are unable to <hi>reduce</hi> thoſe unhappy Souls they had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly led aſtray; and 'tis but too common, that ſuch <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts relapſe</hi> themſelves into thoſe very Errors they had <hi>abjur'd,</hi> and then having by <hi>pretended Repentance</hi> inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated themſelves into the <hi>Churches boſom,</hi> they have the better opportunity to ſcatter their <hi>Poyſon</hi> every where.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who plead for this <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> for the better ſtopping of Mens mouths, are generally wont to diſtinguiſh between <hi>Errors tolerable</hi> and <hi>intolerable;</hi> but which are ſo, or which are not, who ſhall be judge? The Anſwer is preſently by themſelves return'd, <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 8.20.</note> Let Gods Word decide the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, and this is indeed a <hi>certain way.</hi> And yet <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience</hi> tells us, that almoſt every Party pretend the <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture</hi> is on their ſide, and alledge it in defence of their own <hi>Opinions,</hi> when <hi>yet 'tis impoſſible it ſhould he for them All, and every one acknowledges that impoſſibility.</hi> What then is to be determin'd in this caſe? muſt every one be indulg'd in their own way? That is indeed to give them leave to <hi>damn themſelves without controll,</hi> and is ſo contrary to <hi>Chriſtian Charity,</hi> that no <hi>Party when in power was ever yet bad enough to agree to it,</hi> and when in their <hi>depreſt Condition</hi> they cry out loudeſt for <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they are then active and buſie to draw men over to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95396:19"/>their <hi>different Parties</hi> out of tenderneſs, as they alledge, to their Souls; Therefore the <hi>exacteſt Rules</hi> of all <hi>true Policy,</hi> whether <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Civil,</hi> forbids all kind of <hi>Indulgence,</hi> even to thoſe Errors that ſeem in themſelves the moſt <hi>tolerable;</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> are ſo <hi>united</hi> in their <hi>Intereſts</hi> in this Caſe, that what <hi>ruines the one</hi> muſt certainly <hi>confound the other:</hi> The <hi>Word of God</hi> is a Rule to <hi>Princes</hi> as well as others; and <hi>Princes,</hi> if inquiſitive, having better opportunities for Inſtruction, and Souls more vaſt and capable than other Men, may ſoon under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what <hi>Principles</hi> have a due agreement with the <hi>Tenor of Holy Writ,</hi> and what have not, That <hi>Chain of Principles which leads men through all the Actions of Life without oppoſition to any Dictates there, is that to which a Chriſtian Prince is oblig'd to bring men for Gods and for his own ſake, with all that power God has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted him with.</hi> And <hi>unprejudiced Men</hi> by conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Word of God,</hi> and by applying to it the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> of the <hi>Prophets and Apostles</hi> and the <hi>whole primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Christian Church,</hi> as upon Record, may eaſily find out theſe <hi>ſaving Principles;</hi> Thouſands, whoſe Souls are now at reſt, have done it before us: And it is a moſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Truth,</hi> that whereſoever a <hi>Principle diſagreeing to the general ſcope of Scripture</hi> is entertain'd, that very <hi>Principle</hi> will <hi>rend the Church,</hi> and have an unhappy <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence</hi> in due time <hi>upon the State,</hi> nor will the <hi>honeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention</hi> of the Perſon advancing ſuch a Principle be any <hi>ſecurity</hi> either to the one or the other.</p>
            <p>That one Maxim, <hi>That the foundation of Power is originally in the People,</hi> ſeems at firſt very little to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Religion, yet 'tis directly oppoſite to that aſſertion of Gods eternal Wiſdom,<note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> 
               <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes decree Juſtice;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> and to that of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>there is no power but of God, and the powers that be are ordained of God;</hi> and this Tenet, as proper for their turn, <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks</hi> in general own. Now, though I doubt not but many Perſons of very <hi>ſober</hi> and <hi>innocent tempers</hi> have entertain'd that Notion, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in the Belief of it; yet there is no <hi>Rebellion</hi> or <hi>Inſurrection</hi> carry'd on by Man pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſing Chriſtianity, but has been grounded upon and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95396:19"/>aſſerted from that <hi>Principle;</hi> and indeed <hi>Crowns are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſecure things if that be true.</hi> But every one knows, that by how much the <hi>more Innocent</hi> the firſt <hi>Movers</hi> or the great <hi>Promoters</hi> of ſuch Doctrines are, ſo much the greater is the Danger, and the <hi>weakneſs of careleſs and uninquiſitive Perſons</hi> the more eaſily impos'd upon.</p>
            <p>Again, That Opinion that denies <hi>any Power in Church Governours to impoſe indifferent things upon thoſe under their Charge,</hi> ſeems to hold forth a great <hi>deal of Charity,</hi> and yet it's directly contrary to the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> who made <hi>Indifferent Things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15.29,</note> viz. <hi>Abſtinence from things offer'd to Idols, from things ſtrangled, and from Blood, abſolutely neceſſary by their Command.</hi> But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly every truly <hi>compaſſionate</hi> Heart muſt bleed to ſee what <hi>miſerable Fractures and Diviſions</hi> this has made in the Church, how it has been the Common Plea of <hi>Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and has almoſt <hi>vacated all the Laws of God and Man;</hi> For whilſt men oppoſe their <hi>immediate Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> if <hi>Princes</hi> who are to be <hi>nurſing Fathers and nurſing Mothers to the Church</hi> interpoſe, as their Power and Duty engage them, <hi>Ignorant Zeal</hi> preſently breaks out into a <hi>raging Fire,</hi> and creates <hi>Tumults and Diſorders for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and <hi>every one who dies in ſo curst a Cauſe, looks upon himſelf, and is eſteem'd by too many, as a Martyr ſuffering for the Common and dearly purchas'd Liberty of Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Government of the Church by a mixt Body of Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy and Lay Elders,</hi> though it be <hi>Novel</hi> and <hi>Abſurd,</hi> muſt needs be <hi>very plauſible</hi> to the vulgar, <hi>when every Cobler in the Pariſh may hope in time to mate his Landlord or the proudeſt of his Superiours,</hi> and yet <hi>Popery</hi> has nothing in it <hi>more fatal</hi> to the <hi>Thrones of Princes,</hi> than this. Thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuppoſe the <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible,</hi> and from that Suppoſition laid as a Foundation, they rightly enough conclude, <hi>he may depoſe the Higheſt Magiſtrates:</hi> For if the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> be indeed Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible, <hi>he cannot charge a Prince with any other than a real</hi> Sin; <hi>He cannot be miſtaken in his Judgment, and of neceſſity he muſt be Superiour to the greateſt Kings and Emperors under Heaven;</hi> in oppoſition to all this, confute
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95396:20"/>but their <hi>primary Erroneous Hypotheſis,</hi> and the <hi>Blindeſt Romaniſt</hi> will be ſenſible that all his <hi>Concluſions are fooliſh and unwarrantable.</hi> But with thoſe who are for the <hi>Other Government</hi> the Caſe is very different, They declare, <hi>No one Man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſſemb. adv. concerning Conf. of Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1. par. 4.</note> 
               <hi>No Body of Men whatſoever to be Infallible,</hi> and yet though they acknowledge they may err and be miſtaken in their Apprehenſions and Deciſions of things, they are reſolv'd to maintain their <hi>Superiority to all Powers whatſoever;</hi> 'Tis a <hi>ſtanding Rule</hi> with them, <hi>To Diſcipline muſt all the Eſtates in a Kingdom be Subject,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Book of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline c. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Book c. 13.</note> 
               <hi>as well the Rulers, as they that are Ruled:</hi> And this, <hi>Princes and Magiſtrates not being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from Diſcipline,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A third Means whereby they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>verted our People, has been the range and damnable Poſitions, ſuch as, that Subjects do of their own Heads, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much better, than what they do in Obedience to Authority. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can make no Law at all concerning the Church, but only Ratifie what the Church decreeth. It is lawful for Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cts to make a Covenant without the King, and to enter into a Bond of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ual Defence againſt the King and all Perſons whatſoever. An Aſſembly may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>brogate Acts of Parliament if they reflect upon Church Government. The Proteſtation of Subjects againſt Laws eſtabliſh'd, frees them from all Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Obedience to thoſe Laws. <hi>Kings Declar. Annals of Ch. 1. p. 760.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and thoſe that are placed in the Eccleſiaſtical Eſtate, rightly ruling and governing, God ſhall be glorified:</hi> So that though we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them of never ſo many Errors and Corruptions, and prove their Judgments never ſo much miſtaken, there's no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, they are <hi>in the Chair,</hi> and <hi>Right or Wrong</hi> they will Govern. Now where ſuch <hi>fallible Perſons</hi> can <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Supream Magiſtrate,</hi> and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant the <hi>Diſobedience of Subjects,</hi> 'tis in vain to teach <hi>Submiſſion to Civil Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry one looking upon himſelf at ſuch a time as diſpens'd with for <hi>all Vows</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>I need not inſtance in any thing more of this Nature, theſe to unprejudiced Perſons are enough to convince them of the danger of <hi>Indulgence.</hi> Could it have had a good Influence up<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Piety, <hi>Julian the Apoſtate, that ſubtile and inveterate Enemy to Chriſtianity,</hi> would never have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it;<note place="margin">Diſſidentes Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> cum ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be diſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>es me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bat, ut Civilibus diſcordiis C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſopit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nullo vetante Religioni ſue ſerviret intrepidus. Quod agebat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ò obſtinate, ut diſſenſiones augente licentiâ, non timeret unanimantem poſtea plebem: Null<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> beſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ias, ut ſunt ſibi fera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es pleri<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Chriſtianorum expertus <hi>Amnian. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell Lib. 22. cap 5.</hi>
               </note> nay his <hi>own Hiſtorian</hi> aſſures us, That <hi>be recall'd thoſe Christian Biſhops from Exile who had been baniſht by his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle</hi> Conſtantius, <hi>advis'd them to live peaceably,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95396:20"/>and every one elſe to exerciſe their Religion freely, hoping that the Chriſtians by that Indulgence, being animated one againſt another, that Heatheniſm which he deſign'd to reſtore, would meet with the leſs Oppoſition;</hi> And the ſame is confirm'd by the <hi>Church Hiſtorian</hi> in his Account of <hi>Julians Revocation of the baniſh'd Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sozomeni Lib. 5. c. 5.
<p>Deni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tunc <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ddidit Baſileias Haereti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is quando Templa Daemoniis, eo medo putan Chriſtianum nomen poſſe perire de t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rris ſi u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitati Eccleſiae, de quâ lapſus fuerat, invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret &amp; ſacrilegas diſſenſiones liberas eſſe permitteret. <hi>Auguſt. Epiſt. 166.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> And whereas the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> as well as others had their Share in <hi>Julians Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tells them, That <hi>Julian opened Temples to Hereticks and Devils at the ſame time, hoping by that means ſo far to encourage and foment Diſſenſions in it, as thereby at laſt totally to ruin the Church of Chriſt.</hi> And whereas we find <hi>Themiſtius</hi> applauding <hi>Jovian</hi> the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Succeſſor</hi> of <hi>Impious Julian,</hi> for <hi>his Gentleneſs in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting every one to ſerve God according to his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> a Policy very neceſſary in that ſudden Revolution of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs upon the Apoſtates Death. A Learned Man of our own obſerves, That <hi>when the Gentiles were under Hatches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caves Eccles. 2 vol Introd. See. 4. p. 51, 52.</note> 
               <hi>they knew no Means ſo effectual for the keeping Paganiſm alive, as frequent Interceſſions for a Toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing it fit <hi>an Indulgence</hi> ſhould be granted to all perſons of <hi>what Profeſſion</hi> ſoever, I would fain know why the <hi>Extravagancies of Morality</hi> as well as <hi>Divinity</hi> ſhould not be allow'd, why ſhould not <hi>Vice be publickly and legally al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd and protected?</hi> Every one, I know, will exclaim againſt that, and yet <hi>more</hi> may be ſaid for that, than the other. In <hi>Relation to the Church</hi> Vicious Men are <hi>ſcandalous,</hi> yet they never <hi>quarrel about Circumſtances,</hi> or ſtudy to ſet people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the Ears. If they give Offence in <hi>participation of Divine Ordinances,</hi> let them but alone, and they'le never trouble you; they have, <hi>as Vicious,</hi> no <hi>Piques</hi> againſt the <hi>Paſtors of the Church for doing their Duties;</hi> nor do they trouble themſelves in <hi>controverted Doctrines whoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the ſtrongest,</hi> ſo that in the Church, <hi>if tolerated,</hi> they create no <hi>Diſturbance nor begin any Hereſie or Schiſm.</hi> In <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the State,</hi> Let but the <hi>Adulterer enjoy his Whores, the Drunkard his Cups, the Covetous Man his Tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſures.</hi> &amp;c. and, <hi>as ſuch a one,</hi> he'le never engage himſelf in <hi>Plots:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſt the Eſtabliſhed Government, nor pry too buſily into the <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95396:21"/>of Superiors:</hi> But indeed when Men of <hi>theſe Trades, to cloak their Vices, eſpouſe the Intereſts of a Religious Party,</hi> then they <hi>grow dangerous;</hi> for ſince nothing but their <hi>furious Zeal for a Faction,</hi> hinders the World from making <hi>Remarks upon their Shameful Debaucheries,</hi> 'tis their <hi>greateſt Policy</hi> to ſhew enough of <hi>that;</hi> by this means, after their <hi>firm Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure with Malecontents and Schiſmaticks,</hi> how many <hi>ſoft and gentle Words</hi> are found out to <hi>extenuate their Crimes!</hi> So that <hi>He that is loaded with all the Wickedneſs Hell can furniſh for him, while he Heads a Party, ſhall be accounted, though a frail and frequently tempted, yet a very ſincere and well-meaning Brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if at laſt we look into the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we ſhall find that as he has commanded us to <hi>abſtain from all Immoralities,</hi> even from <hi>whatſoever has the leaſt appearance of Evil;</hi> ſo he has by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> enjoy'd us <hi>To mark,</hi> to ſet a Brand of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy upon <hi>thoſe which cauſe Diviſions and Offences contrary to the Doctrine we have learn'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.22.</note> 
               <hi>and to avoid them, for they that are ſuch, ſerve not our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but their own Belly, and by good Words and fair Speeches deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 16.17, 18.</note> It is not the <hi>openneſs of a Sin</hi> that makes it <hi>comparatively the greater; Malice</hi> is as bad as <hi>Theft,</hi> yet it lies cloſe <hi>conceal'd</hi> within the dark Receſſes of the Soul: <hi>Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,</hi> is an obſcure Sin, few know what it is, yet every one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves it worſe than <hi>Drunkenneſs, Adultery, Covetouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Treaſon,</hi> though it <hi>hates the Light,</hi> is as bad as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs:</hi> To <hi>curſe the King in our Hearts,</hi> though never ſo ſecretly, is a <hi>damnable Sin,</hi> and 'tis the ſame to <hi>contrive Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults and Rebellion in the State;</hi> but theſe laſt admit of one <hi>particular Aggravation</hi> beyond all <hi>bare Immoralities</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: and it's this, <hi>Every one who pretends to Conſcience acknowledges his Duty to abjure all Immoralities, while ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pretend to be active in the other only for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and when <hi>Sin</hi> is once <hi>abetted</hi> by that which Men call <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> the miſchievous Effects of it know no Bounds.</p>
            <p>Let us then ſuppoſe theſe Samaritans had been ſo far enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd and indulg'd by the Jews, as <hi>to have built the Temple with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem, to have ſet up their Synagogues, gather'd their Congregations, and preach'd their own Doctrines among them without Controul,</hi> what muſt have been the event, would not <hi>Gods Law have ſoon been thruſt out of doors? Truth</hi> indeed is
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95396:21"/>the moſt <hi>Ancient,</hi> but <hi>Novelty</hi> is the moſt <hi>pleaſing to Itching Ears,</hi> and therefore thoſe <hi>Jews</hi> who would have been frequent Spectators of the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Rites, would too eaſily have been drawn to approve and practiſe what they had ſeen; the <hi>Jews</hi> had prov'd this before to their Smart, when a <hi>bare permiſſion</hi> of ſome of the <hi>Old Canaanites</hi> to live among them, drew themſelves, the Lords peculiar Inheritance to <hi>Abominable Idolatries.</hi> But ſince their Law gave no ſuch <hi>Liberty</hi> to the <hi>Jews,</hi> we may aſſure our ſelves our <hi>Saviour</hi> came not to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe any <hi>ſuch Liberty</hi> for us; a <hi>Redemption from the ſlavery of Sin</hi> God ſhadow'd out in the <hi>Moſaick diſpenſation;</hi> and <hi>our Saviour with his own moſt precious Blood purchas'd for us Chriſtians a freedom from Sin,</hi> but no <hi>Toleration</hi> to do what we pleaſe, or to <hi>Worſhip God</hi> according to our own <hi>Fancies. I doubt not but God has permitted pretences to</hi> Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>to end generally in Inſurrections and Rebellions, to render the pretenders to it odious to all conſiderable perſons, and to compel Civil Magiſtrates, if not for Gods, yet for their own ſakes to ſuppreſs them.</hi> I ſhall conclude this Obſervation with the words of the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines;</hi>
               <q>They who upon pretence of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> ſhall oppoſe any lawful Power, or the Lawful Exerciſe of it, whether it be Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, reſiſt the Ordinance of God; and for their publiſhing ſuch Opinions, and maintaining ſuch practices as are contrary to the light of Nature, or the known Principles of Chriſtianity, whether concerning <hi>Faith, Worſhip, Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation,</hi> or the <hi>power of Godlineſs,</hi> or ſuch erroneous Opinions or Practices, as either in their own Nature, or in the manner of publiſhing and maintaining them are deſtructive to the External Peace and Order,<note place="margin">Aſſembl. adv. about Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, c. 20. par. 4.</note> which Chriſt hath eſtabliſht in the Church, they may lawfully be call'd to Account, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt by the Cenſures of the Church, and by the power of the Civil Magiſtrate, &amp; therefore not to be indulg'd.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a Refuſal of the Aſſiſtance exaſperates the Churches Enemies, and puts them upon all,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obſerv. 5.</note> 
               <hi>even the moſt deſperate Courſes to hinder that good work which by other means they could not.</hi> This we learn from the practice of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> here in the Text, Becauſe their Offer was rejected, <hi>they weakned the hands of the People, and troubled them in build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hired Councellors againſt them.</hi> And here the <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite</hi> ſhews himſelf, he cannot bear a <hi>Repulſe,</hi> eſpecially ſuch a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95396:22"/>one as entrenches upon his high flying Piety, without a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengeful mind.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 15.21, — 28.</note> The poor <hi>Syrophoenician Woman in the Goſpel</hi> could endure it from our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and very <hi>ſevere Language</hi> with it, and yet would not leave him till ſhe obtain'd her Requeſt, and it was becauſe ſhe was ſincere and honeſt in her heart: But ſome <hi>pretending Diſciples</hi> of our Saviour, who thought <hi>highly of themſelves,</hi> when they heard but one <hi>hard Saying,</hi> and that ſpoken that every one might be able to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between <hi>thoſe that believ'd,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 6.64, 66.</note> 
               <hi>and thoſe that believ'd not,</hi> they took Snuff at it, <hi>went back and walk'd no more with him. Hypocriſie</hi> always flies out upon the <hi>leaſt ſuſpicion</hi> into <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance,</hi> 'its too tender to endure a ſevere touch, and it yet wants no <hi>Impudence</hi> on its part; for take <hi>perſons</hi> guilty of it in a <hi>declining ſtate,</hi> nothing concerns them then but the <hi>great and general decay of true Piety</hi> (to which yet they themſelves above all others contribute) <hi>the impending ruine of Religion, the Coldneſs, the Formality, the Superſtition of Profeſſors;</hi> and who would not think at ſuch a time that their <hi>tongues were toucht with a Coal from the ſacred Altar?</hi> who would not be ready at firſt to believe ſuch Perſons rather rejected for their <hi>Innocence</hi> and out of <hi>Envy,</hi> than for any juſt or <hi>real Cauſe?</hi> Thus does <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> riſe high in the <hi>Vogue of the People,</hi> and the <hi>worſt of men</hi> paſs for the moſt <hi>zealous Chriſtians;</hi> and thus do <hi>State Politicians</hi> thrown from the management of publick Affairs for their <hi>Ill deſerts,</hi> as if yet all depended upon their concern in the Government, make their loud <hi>Complaints</hi> among ſuch as are willing to be deceiv'd, of <hi>Tyranny, Oppreſſion, Arbitrary and Illegal Impoſitions,</hi> as if none but themſelves had been <hi>the true Patriots and Aſſertors of their Countries Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Put the ſame Perſons into <hi>another ſtate</hi> and preſently they run into <hi>another ſtrein,</hi> let them have the <hi>Power</hi> and down go all their <hi>Opponents</hi> right or wrong; what, <hi>are they not ſure they are in the Right way to Heaven? are not all things among them form'd according to the pattern in the Mount? And can they to whom God has committed the management of Affairs ſee Men running headlong into the Methods of Error and Eternal ruine without Compaſſion, or without endeavouring to compel Men to come in and be ſaved? And muſt not the multitude of Diſſenters in Religious matters weaken the hands of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, hinder the Exaltation of Chriſt upon his Throne,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95396:22"/>and expoſe that Common-wealth to innumerable hazards, whereof Providence has made them the Fathers and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors?</hi> None but <hi>Atheiſts</hi> certainly can deny this, or <hi>Men of their</hi> own temper, when by driving <hi>Phaeton</hi> like they have precipitated themſelves from their <hi>abus'd Command,</hi> for then, perhaps, they begin to relent, to acknowledge themſelves to <hi>have been but men,</hi> and ſo by reaſon of their <hi>carnal minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to have miſcarried fouly in theſe things; but ſtill they plead that others ought not to follow their unhappy Examples, but the rather to inſiſt in the Methods of <hi>Charity</hi> and <hi>Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>wretched Hypocrites</hi> twiſt and wind themſelves every way, yet by all their ſtruggling do but entangle them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the more; and yet by <hi>ſuch thin</hi> and <hi>ſilly</hi> Arts as theſe they creep into the Affections of the <hi>raſh</hi> and <hi>inconſiderate,</hi> by theſe means they manage <hi>Parties in Religion and Policy,</hi> and in the <hi>midſt of Diviſions reign Triumphant;</hi> by theſe means they find opportunities to inſtil <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> into the minds of Men, and by the <hi>numbers of their Admirers</hi> to terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the builders of Gods Church: thus <hi>Religion</hi> it ſelf is by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees deſtroy'd, and the deſigns and endeavours of Gods moſt faithful Servants fruſtrated. Theſe <hi>Enemies of Truth</hi> know well, <hi>that fear is a betrayer of all Counſels,</hi> and makes men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for any work; the <hi>Samaritans</hi> try'd the Experiment, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> was told concerning them,<note place="margin">Nehem. 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>From all places whence ye ſhall return to us, They will be upon you;</hi> They ſet a <hi>Prophet</hi> to perſwade <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to fly into the <hi>Temple for his ſecurity,</hi> whoſe fear would have diſcouraged all the reſt, and plied him with Ill news and ſcandalous ſtories. He gives the reaſon of their acting thus, <hi>For they All made us afraid, ſaying,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nehem. 6.9.</note> 
               <hi>Their hands ſhall be weakned from the work that it be not done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Were but Men ſo good as they ſhould be, the Artifices of Gods Enemies could not have ſuch miſchievous effects upon them, <hi>they would not be afraid of any evil Tidings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.7.</note> 
               <hi>their hearts ſtanding faſt in the Lord.</hi> This great defect makes every <hi>Idle rumor,</hi> every <hi>vain fancy</hi> terrible, ſo that the moſt <hi>ſteady,</hi> the moſt <hi>deliberate</hi> and <hi>rational Methods of Honouring God</hi> may by malicious Men be traduced, and they by careleſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons believ'd; and ſo thoſe come to be charged with <hi>Innovating Humors,</hi> who above all <hi>oppoſe Innovations;</hi> and thoſe who cannot relinquiſh that Religion they have taken up upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible grounds, are ſtil'd <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> Fear repreſenting every
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95396:23"/>object contrary to what indeed it is, and bringing us within danger of their Curſe <hi>who call evil good and good evil;</hi> 'tis counted Madneſs for a man to <hi>kill himſelf for fear of dying,</hi> ſuch a <hi>Madneſs</hi> thoſe fall into <hi>who loſe their Religion for fear of loſing it,</hi> who are ſollicitous about it till they forget what it really conſiſts in, and then engage in endleſs quarrels about Circumſtances, as if the Shadow were of any value, when the Body, or when the ſolid Subſtance is gone.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Men yet who are <hi>pure Politicians,</hi> who aim at their own profit or grandure, without reſpect to Religion or the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, prove excellent Inſtruments to carry on their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns who <hi>ſtudy to diſturb Gods Church.</hi> If thoſe Enemies be <hi>few and inconſiderable,</hi> they may perhaps <hi>let them alone;</hi> but if they be <hi>many</hi> and <hi>perſons of Intereſt or Wealth,</hi> the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in the head of them, and <hi>whiſpering ſtories</hi> on their behalf in the <hi>Ears of Princes</hi> engages the whole Party on their ſide, who trouble not themſelves ſo much about <hi>Faith</hi> as about <hi>Practice,</hi> and therefore believe the greateſt <hi>Atheiſt</hi> that is but on their ſide to be <hi>a Child of Light</hi> though <hi>walking in Darkneſs:</hi> And indeed the only certain means for <hi>Capital Debauchees</hi> to get any Reputation for goodneſs, is to cloſe with diſaffected and malicious Hypocrites, which (if many perſons are not in a very groſs Error) does, like that true <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> recommended to us by the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Jam. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>cover a multitude of Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 'tis remarkable, that when <hi>Princes out of Zeal for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> make the beſt proviſion for its defence that <hi>Humane Providence</hi> can reach to, ſome are ſo curiouſly ſubtile, as to endeavour at leaſt, to make their <hi>Laws</hi> like Spiders Webs, ſo tender, that every <hi>daring Spirit</hi> may, without danger, <hi>break through them;</hi> and ſometimes they try to turn their edge from thoſe they were deſign'd againſt, to thoſe in whoſe favour they were made, and many more Devices are daily found out to the <hi>terror of Well-doers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heſiod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>but to the praiſe of them that do evil;</hi> ſuch ſhall never want employment; for thoſe who when they are angry at Heaven, would go to Hell it ſelf to proſecute their Revenge, will never miſs any help they can find on Earth. But while wicked Men enraged at their diſappointments turn every way to work miſchief, they fall upon the Poets Truth †, <hi>They draw the greateſt miſchiefs upon their own heads, by their own contrivances, and ruine themſelves with their own Arts;</hi> for
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95396:23"/>thoſe who move in an <hi>higher Sphere,</hi> though wicked as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, regard their Faction but as Steps to mount by, which may afterwards be burnt, and therefore thoſe <hi>Leaders</hi> thruſt them upon all <hi>deſperate Actions,</hi> till from <hi>Malice, Murmuring</hi> and <hi>Sedition,</hi> they riſe to <hi>Riots</hi> and <hi>Rebellions,</hi> trying ſo to <hi>wreſt</hi> that by force out of the hands of their Superiors, which by <hi>ſubtile Flatteries</hi> they cannot attain to; wherein if they ſucceed, though they make themſelves <hi>perfect Slaves</hi> by the bargain, yet the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>great Object of their Spleen,</hi> muſt be ſure to ſuffer, and <hi>while their Leaders triumph, the Temples building muſt ceaſe, and</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>continue but an heap of Stones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having laid down theſe Obſervations,<note place="margin">Applic.</note> I ſhall at laſt for <hi>Application</hi> ſhew the <hi>unhappy Paralleliſm between the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and the Engliſh Church,</hi> in reſpect of the Practices of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> againſt theirs of the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> of all ſorts againſt our Peace, and the <hi>Reſtauration of Gods ancient, ſolemn, and publick Worſhip</hi> among us: To this end</p>
            <p>Let us look back to the <hi>firſt Reformation of Religion</hi> in this Kingdom, when it was laid for a ſure foundation, <hi>That we ſhould forſake the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>only ſo far as that had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the Rule of Gods Word.</hi> And it's notoriouſly evident, <hi>That whoſoever out of one pretence or other ſhould go further, muſt inſtead of oppoſing real Popery cloſe with it, running himſelf upon the ſame Crime of bidding defiance to, and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeding the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> When God of his infinite mercy was pleas'd after that <hi>long and diſmal Night of Popiſh Ignorance and Superſtition</hi> to give us a <hi>Prince</hi> who favour'd the <hi>pure and undiſguis'd Truth,</hi> thoſe <hi>whoſe Hearts God had touch'd,</hi> ſet earneſtly upon that great work of <hi>Gratitude,</hi> the reſtoring Gods ſacred Temple, or the ſettling God, Worſhip within theſe Kingdoms; not according to the <hi>Pattern of other Reformers,</hi> but that of the <hi>truly Ancient, Catholick and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church of Chriſt,</hi> which they had a greater advantage of doing than others, for that the <hi>lawful Supream Authority</hi> of the Kingdom <hi>concur'd</hi> with and <hi>encouraged</hi> them in their endeavours. And they proceeded in their work with ſuch care, that Dr. <hi>Taylor,</hi> a Martyr in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days, declares of the Church Service as then reform'd, <hi>that it was ſo fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected according to the Rules of our Chriſtian Religion in every behalf,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts and Men, Tom. 3. p. 131.</note> 
               <hi>that no Chriſtian Conſcience could be offended with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing contain'd therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:95396:24"/>When a new <hi>Cloud of Popery</hi> rais'd by a <hi>bigot Queen</hi> was by Gods goodneſs diſpell'd, and <hi>Queen Elizabeth</hi> peaceably ſettled upon the Throne, the <hi>Purification of Divine Worſhip</hi> from thoſe <hi>foul Accretions</hi> which had faſten'd on it in her Siſters days, was one of the firſt things they ſet upon; and whereas <hi>K.</hi> Edward<hi>'s Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity had been by Q.</hi> Mary <hi>repeal'd to the great decay of the true Honour of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, 1 Eliz.</note> 
               <hi>and diſcomfort to the Profeſſors of the truth of Chriſts Religion.</hi> She again by Act of Parliament reſettled that almoſt loſt form of Worſhip,<note place="margin">Calv. Cecillio Anglo.</note> and to this very work <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf excites, as he tells Sir <hi>W. Cecill</hi> afterwards Lord <hi>Burghly,</hi> whom by an Epiſtle he perſwades to advance the ſame Work with all his power; and he that ſhall compare that <hi>Epiſtle of his to the Duke of</hi> Somerſet <hi>when Protector, with this,</hi> will find him a ſtrong ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prover of that <hi>very Method</hi> our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelates inſiſted in in their Reformation: The maintaining of Gods Worſhip ſo ſettl'd has been the work of ſucceeding Princes, wherein <hi>CHARLES the Martyr of Glorious Memory</hi> was Inferior to none.</p>
            <p>More <hi>Black,</hi> more <hi>Bloody</hi> and <hi>terrible</hi> yet was that <hi>gloomy Night of Confuſion and Rebellion that enſued;</hi> but it pleas'd God, the great worker of Miracles, to produce <hi>Light</hi> once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain out of <hi>horrid Darkneſs,</hi> to reſtore our <hi>Sovereign to his Throne,</hi> and our <hi>Biſhops and Curates to the Church</hi> as at firſt. A task they had no leſs hard than that of <hi>Judas Maccabeus</hi> of old,<note place="margin">1 Mace. 4.36. — 61.</note> to purifie thoſe Temples once dedicated to Gods Honour; but then <hi>miſerably profan'd</hi> by the <hi>impure devotions of time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Enthuſiaſts and Rebels,</hi> then was the <hi>Nations Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude</hi> to God for that <hi>never to be forgotten Mercy,</hi> duly expreſt by renewing the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity of Common-Prayer and Service in the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, 14 Car. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and Adminiſtration of the Sacraments, for the better ſecuring divine Bleſſings to us for the future:</hi> And this Order is now ſettled among us by ſo <hi>good Laws,</hi> confirm'd by ſo <hi>irrefragable Authority,</hi> ſecur'd by ſuch excellent <hi>Rules and Canons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Corbets</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys</hi> Speeches in the Account of their Deaths, p 54<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 56. See <hi>Burnet</hi>'s Hiſt. of Ref. v. 2. Preface, p. 16, 17.</note> that even by the <hi>Confeſſion of our greateſt Enemies, our Church and Nation is the Envy of our Neighbours, the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark and glory of the Reformation.</hi> And the <hi>Regular and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Clergy,</hi> are generally ſo faithful to the <hi>Intereſt of the true Religion as eſtabliſh'd among us by Law,</hi> and ſo well able to aſſert it againſt all <hi>Gainſayers,</hi> that while any regard is had by the People to them we need not run out of our Wits for fear of Innovations.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:95396:24"/>In <hi>three Revolutions</hi> then our caſe has been paralel with that of the <hi>Jews;</hi> we have been Captives to our inſulting Enemies as well as they, and every return from Captivity has been ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated with the Reſtauration of Gods truly Ancient Worſhip and Service. But we have had <hi>Samaritans</hi> too, Perſons who have by all the Methods of <hi>Subtilty</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> oppos'd that <hi>Glorious Work;</hi> That the <hi>Zealots of the Church of Rome</hi> ſhould eſpouſe her <hi>Intereſt,</hi> &amp; endeavour to reenſlave theſe Churches to <hi>Superſtition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> is no wonder; but that Perſons who pretend the <hi>greateſt Hatred to that Religion</hi> ſhould joyn with its Favourers, ſhould <hi>promote and extend its Doctrines,</hi> ſhould <hi>imitate its worſt and moſt Unchriſtian Practices,</hi> was very ſtrange! But again, to abate of that wonder, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that thoſe Perſons who concluded <hi>every thing unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and execrable that had been us'd in the time of Popery, and conſequently to be rejected,</hi> ſhould have any real good will to the Reformation; Reaſon tells us, <hi>That the abuſe of a thing, though never ſo groſs, cannot alter its firſt or Original nature.</hi> Our Saviour himſelf ſubmitted to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Rites <hi>that he might fulfil all righteouſneſs;</hi> though <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law had been as much <hi>adulterated</hi> among the <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 3.15.</note> as that of <hi>Chriſt</hi> among <hi>Papiſts:</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did not reject every <hi>Ceremony</hi> or <hi>Circumſtance</hi> that had been <hi>abus'd</hi> by the <hi>Heathens.</hi> All which may inform us, that thoſe who uſe ſuch Arguments againſt <hi>Conſtitutions lawful in themſelves,</hi> as <hi>their former abuſe,</hi> can aim at nothing by ſo doing, but only a general Diſorder and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>It was indeed the <hi>Maſter-Piece</hi> of <hi>Roman Policy,</hi> to ſcatter the Seeds of <hi>Diviſion</hi> and <hi>Separation</hi> among us, and to bring men into conceit againſt all <hi>public Order</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> and they began this Practice betimes, ſome few there were that from prejudices contracted by forreign Converſation oppos'd ſome appointments of the Church in K. <hi>Edward</hi> the 6ths <hi>days;</hi> but their Scruples were of little concern, &amp; the Effects of their oppoſition were prevented by Qu. <hi>Maries</hi> Perſecution: But it was an ill <hi>Omen</hi> of what might follow, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Exiles at <hi>Frankford</hi> ſhould quarrel about the form of Gods Worſhip, and <hi>Knox,</hi> the <hi>Head of the Schiſmatical party,</hi> be ſo early and yet juſtly accus'd of Treaſon againſt the <hi>German</hi> Emperor: When thoſe who had created diſturbance there return'd home
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95396:25"/>in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign, they brought ſo much of a <hi>pervicacious humor</hi> along with them, that though they fell not themſelves into direct ſeparation from the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet they laid the <hi>curſed foundations</hi> of thoſe <hi>fatal differences</hi> we have ever ſince groan'd under; the <hi>Parties</hi> were but <hi>few</hi> in thoſe days, but that prudent Queen was ſo well convinc'd of the Influence their Novel and diſorderly conceits then vented, muſt have upon the State, that no perſwaſions (though from her greateſt Favourites) could reconcile her to them; and yet the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> their Succeſſors, in theſe days, proclaim her <hi>no friend to Popery.</hi> He that reads the Authentic ſtory of <hi>Faithful</hi> Commin <hi>the Romiſh Prieſt,</hi> the great <hi>Patron of Phanaticiſm</hi> in thoſe days,<note place="margin">Foxes and Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands by <hi>Nal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Camdens Ann. Eliz. 1588.</note> and of <hi>Heath</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> afterwards, with the <hi>Principles they acted upon,</hi> and obſerves the practices of <hi>Hacket, Coppinger, Arthington and others,</hi> with the <hi>boldneſs</hi> of <hi>Barrow, Penry,</hi> and other <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Factors for Puritaniſm</hi> in that age, will be eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd, that a <hi>well regulated Monarchy</hi> can never proſper where ſuch <hi>Incendiaries</hi> are indulg'd; <hi>Incendiaries</hi> I may well call them, for in the <hi>Reign</hi> of <hi>CHARLES</hi> the <hi>Firſt</hi> their ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Opinions and Practices, propagated to their Poſterity, prevail'd ſo far as to ſet <hi>Three flouriſhing Kingdoms in a flame,</hi> to the ruine of <hi>Law, Liberty, Religion,</hi> and whatſoever could be dear to Men or Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The ſeveral <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> the <hi>Pretenders to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences</hi> in former days were engag'd in, receiv'd their <hi>Conſummation</hi> at laſt in that <hi>great and tragical Rebellion;</hi> and it was no wonder that <hi>Rebellion</hi> ſhould follow upon that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>That Princes were accountable for their miſcarriages to their own Subjects;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dangerous Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, p. 14.</note> 
               <hi>That their Subjects in caſe of their Neglect might reform Religion, without and in oppoſition to them; and that the Church of</hi> England <hi>was then ſo miſerably corrupted both in Doctrine and Diſcipline, that a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was abſolutely neceſſary.</hi> Doctrines which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Primitive Chriſtians</hi> were abſolutely unacquainted with, and which the <hi>wiſeſt Men</hi> ſaw no neceſſity of, which Doctrines were all of them confirm'd in that <hi>curſed Covenant</hi> 
               <note n="†" place="margin">The Covenant was receiv'd by Papiſts with infinite Joy, as hoping that now the time was come in which both we and our Succeſſors might be brought to abhor and deteſt that Religion, whoſe profeſt Zealots had been the Authors of ſuch an unſufferable Covenant, which could not conſiſt with Monarchy, which appear'd to us moſt evidently by the Advertiſements ſent up to us by ſome of our Council of <hi>Scotland,</hi> that the ſudden and frequent arrival of Prieſts and Jeſuits from <hi>Doway,</hi> and other Seminaries beyond the Seas, was ſo great in hope of their welcom to us, becauſe of this Seditions Covenant, &amp;c. With Proteſtants abroad it was receiv'd with moſt offenſive ſcandal and infinite grief, which appear'd to us by advertiſement from ſome of our Public Miniſters abroad, who certifi'd us that both the Miniſters and others of their Conſiſtory at <hi>Charenton,</hi> and of other refom'd Churches in <hi>France,</hi> as alſo the Profeſſors, Miniſters and Conſiſtory at <hi>Geneva,</hi> and of other neighbouring reform'd Churches in thoſe Parts, were ſo ſcandaliz'd with this prodigious Covenant, as that they were afraid of nothing more than this, That it would bring an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Scandal upon the reform'd Churches, and alienate the Minds of all the Princes of Chriſtendom from ever entertaining a good thought of their Religion. <hi>His Majeſties Narrative of</hi> Scotch <hi>Tumults, 1683.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous to all perſons of all Religions,</hi> and the <hi>Effect of ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95396:25"/>laid open to the aſtoniſhed World. Then it was that <hi>Indulgence</hi> indeed prevail'd, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in thoſe Days with reaſon enough pleaded for themſelves, <hi>That all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution for Religion was clearly repugnant to thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Freedom ſo often and ſolemuly declar'd by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Army,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt. Modern. par. 2. p. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally receiv'd by all the moderate and well temper'd People in the Nation;</hi> and then it was propounded to the remnant of the Commons at <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter, That all ſuch as profeſs Faith in God by Jeſus Christ, however differing in Judgment from the Doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>'s Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>word, p. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Worſhip and Diſcipline publickly held forth, ſhould not be reſtrain'd from, but protected in the profeſſion of their Faith, and exerciſe of their Religion according to their Conſcience;</hi> according to which Propoſition all kind of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies were to be maintain'd and defended by Public Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. And thus Gods <hi>ſolemn Worſhip</hi> was overturn'd, and the <hi>Liturgy of the Church of England</hi> laid aſide; about which I may uſe our Churches words, <hi>By what undue means, and for what miſchievous purpoſes the uſe of that Liturgy (though enjoyn'd by the Laws of the Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preface to Common Prayer.</note> 
               <hi>and thoſe Laws unrepeal'd) came during the late unhappy Confuſions to be diſcontinued, is too well known to the World, and we are not willing to remember; But when upon his Majesties happy Reſtauration it ſeem'd probable, that among other things the uſe of the Liturgy alſo would return of Courſe (the ſame having never been legally aboliſh'd) unleſs ſome timely means were us'd to prevent it; thoſe Men who, under the late uſurp't Powers, had made it a great part of their buſineſs to render the People diſaffected thereunto, ſaw themſelves in point of Reputation and Interest, concern'd with their utmoſt endeavours to hinder its restitution.</hi> Hence it came that the Pamphlets of former days, were
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95396:26"/>ſeconded by <hi>Petitions for Peace, Neceſſity of Reformation, &amp;c. Our publick Forms of Worſhip</hi> expos'd to contempt with all the <hi>Scurrility and Satyrical Virulency</hi> imaginable; their Books of <hi>Prodigies,</hi> parallel to the <hi>Romiſh Golden Legends,</hi> ſtuff'd with <hi>Lies</hi> prodigious as the <hi>Stories</hi> related, and all printed but to make the Vulgar run mad; and all other <hi>inſinuating Arts</hi> were made uſe of, that even the <hi>great Council of the Nations</hi> might be made <hi>Abettors of an Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and multiform Faction,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Laws,</hi> whereby the true Religion is ſecur'd to us, be <hi>repeal'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>While thoſe Devices have ſail'd, they have tryed another way; and as if the Nation had nothing to fear but <hi>Popery,</hi> they have declaim'd loudly againſt that: and as if the <hi>Legal Clergy</hi> were too weak to cope with the <hi>Goliaths of Rome,</hi> they forſooth, have been very forward to lend their helping Hand, where indeed they could only prove, as <hi>Rabſhaketh told Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> would do, <hi>A mere ſtaff of a bruiſed Reed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Kings 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.21.</note> 
               <hi>on which if a man lean'd, it would go into his hand and pierce it;</hi> or as the Samaritans to the Jews, <hi>Betrayers, not Aſſiſtants.</hi> To prove which in its largeſt ſenſe, I ſhall only give you the Character of the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> one principal Party among the Adverſaries of the Church of <hi>England</hi> as by Law eſtabliſh'd, drawn by a <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>Diſſenting Tribe, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> ſays he, <hi>never walks ſo ſecure as under the Cloak of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, hence it is that the Pope makes uſe of thoſe Reverend Foxes the Jeſuits to diſguiſe and agitate his Affairs: But what a miſery is it that the Jeſuits, ſpued out of other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeem to have taken Sanctuary in ours, walking up and down with the Garb and Title of Proteſtant Miniſters? For the carrying on their Traiterous Deſigns they have far out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtripp'd the Jeſuits both in Practice and Project, they have not only tamper'd with mens Conſciences in private, but they preach open Rebellion and Treaſon with a full Mouth in the Pulpit; they hold Correſpondence with the Enemies abroad and with Aſſociates of their own Humour and Faction at home, acting their Conſpiracies in the form and authority of a Body Politick, preſuming to Commiſſionate Agents, give out Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, treat with the Publick Enemy, raiſe Money to carry on the Confederacy, to which end they have their private Conſults Eaſts, and Contributions, which in caſe of Diſcovery, they ſay
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95396:26"/>were intended for the Good of the Nation and for Charitable <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</hi> This, though written 30 years ſince, looks like the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Separatiſts</hi> at this time: but he adds further; <hi>The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of breeding up their Proſelites is far more ſerpentine and ſubtile than that of the Jeſuits for qualifying their Novices; For</hi> 1. <hi>They initiate them with Faſtings, ſolemn Vows and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Sermons and Sacraments, and ſo all the Ordinances of God are proſtituted with the greater Reverence to enchant and bind their Confederates.</hi> 2. <hi>They are inſtructed in the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd Myſteries of Equivocating and Mental Reſervation.</hi> 3dly. <hi>They are taught never to Confeſs when Examin'd, or to elude their Confeſſion; which Principles being allow'd, it's impoſſible for any Commonwealth to be ſecure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mercurius Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus, <hi>June</hi> 19. 1651.</note> 
               <hi>or that Juſtice can have its Courſe againſt Conſpirators and Traitors;</hi> Thus far that Author, <hi>a Prophet indeed.</hi> He that ſhall compare this with <hi>Oates's Narrative</hi> and <hi>The Peaceable Deſign Renew'd,</hi> muſt needs conclude theſe would be excellent <hi>Champions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Popery;</hi> And whoſoever will take the pains to read his late <hi>Majeſties Narrative of the Scotch Tumults,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paragr. 1.35, 43.</note> and the <hi>Scotch Proteſtation againſt Marqueſs</hi> Hamilton <hi>his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner,</hi> will find that is the buſineſs of the <hi>leading Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> not to beat down but to <hi>confirm and aggravate the groſſeſt Errors in Popery,</hi> as I intimated before. To confirm which, I ſhall add that <hi>Monſtrous Poſition</hi> laid down in the forenamed Proteſtation about <hi>Oaths,</hi> viz. <hi>That the ſwearer is neither bound to the meaning of him that exacts the Oath, nor to his own meaning who takes the Oath, but to the reality of the thing ſworn, as it ſhall be afterwards at any time explicated by the Competent Judge:</hi> which Poſition once granted,<note place="margin">Annals of King <hi>Charles</hi> p. 726.</note> it's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for any one to know what he ſwears to in the moſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Oath he takes.</p>
            <p>So unfit are theſe Perſons to be admitted to build with us the Church of God, Yet the <hi>Diſſenters of all Sorts</hi> plead their <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with us in Religion:</hi> 'Tis often urged by their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, that their <hi>Religion is the ſame</hi> in Subſtance with ours, they <hi>receive our Articles,</hi> own <hi>our Doctrines, receive Gods Word,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Colledge, the late Proteſtant Martyr,</hi> as he is eſteem'd by ſome, expreſſes himſelf very like the Samaritans in the Text, <hi>I have been a Lover of the Church of</hi> England,<note place="margin">Tryal of Coll. p. 79.</note> ſays he, <hi>and of all the Fundamental Points of Doctrine believ'd in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95396:27"/>it, I own the ſame God, the ſame Saviour, the ſame Faith, the ſame Goſpel.</hi> But Pleas of this Nature would not ſerve turn, <hi>Our Soveraign and the Fathers of our Church</hi> could not in prudence admit of ſuch <hi>Petitions for Peace,</hi> as were indeed the loud <hi>Alarms to War,</hi> nor receive thoſe whoſe <hi>hands had been ſo deep in the Blood of the late Wars,</hi> to joyn in the <hi>Reſtoring Gods Holy Worſhip</hi> without ſuch an <hi>Abjuration</hi> of their former Errors, as might give the World ſome <hi>reaſonable ſatisfaction,</hi> which <hi>they</hi> knew not how to ſubmit to: They foreſaw their <hi>Fanatick Deſign</hi> well enough, and that all the World might ſee it too, ſince <hi>our Soveraigns Miraculous Reſtauration,</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have laid it open enough.</p>
            <p>They have ſince that Time made it their Buſineſs to inſtil the <hi>foremention'd Principles</hi> into the Minds of Men, and have added others of the ſame dangerous Nature: <hi>No Popery, no Slavery,</hi> has been the Common Cry, they acting therein like thoſe <hi>Subtile Villains,</hi> who when they have kill'd a Man themſelves, are the moſt buſie to find out the <hi>Murderers.</hi> Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs have the <hi>Pamphlets Invective</hi> againſt the <hi>eſtabliſh'd Government both in Church and State</hi> been; <hi>The King, his Council, the Clergy</hi> have been continually expos'd to the <hi>hatred and ſcorn of the People;</hi> and ſome have ventur'd boldly to charge their <hi>Repreſentatives in Parliament</hi> to <hi>turn all things <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſide-down:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vox Pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iae. Addreſſes to the new choſen Members. Colledges Tryal p. 82.</note> Nor have <hi>Seditious Satyrs</hi> againſt the preſent Government ſufficed, but the late <hi>Horrid Rebellion</hi> has been <hi>juſtified, &amp; Plots and Conſpiracies for a new Rebellion form'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preſently after the Reſtauration of his Sacred Majeſty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore things were ſully ſettled, <hi>Tong, Phillips, Stubs, Hind, Sallers, Gibbs,</hi> all Men pretending to tender Conſciences were executed at <hi>Tyburn Dec.</hi> 22.—62. for no meaner a Deſign, than <hi>Cutting off Root and Branch, Kings, Queens, Dukes, Biſhops, all were to go one way; That there ſhould be no Running be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, or Parle is there, but a Total Deſtruction of Kings, Lords, Biſhops and Gentry;</hi> the Plot when effected, to be <hi>Charged upon the Papiſts,</hi> and the People to be excited to riſe in Arms under pretence of a <hi>Popiſh Maſſacre,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See the Tryals printed 1662. Narr. p. laſt. Tryal p. 12.</note> and that by means of a <hi>Seditious Letter</hi> deſign'd to be diſpers'd in the Country, the Copy of which was then produc'd in Court; and 'tis remarkable that all Intereſts, <hi>Fifth-Monarchy-Men, Figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Quakers, Anabaptiſts, Independents,</hi> were eaſily agreed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95396:27"/>in this Glorious Attempt, and the Grime was confeſt by them all at the Place of Execution. But the <hi>Godly Party</hi> were not ſo to be frighted, the Year following they were <hi>plotting again</hi> in the Northern Parts, to carry on the ſame Work their <hi>Brethren</hi> had fail'd in before, of which <hi>Treaſonable Plot</hi> his Majeſty tells the two Houſes, <hi>That it was of a large Extent and very near Execution,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kings Speech March. 21. 1663. 4.</note> 
               <hi>had not He by Gods Goodneſs come to the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the principal Contrivers, and ſo ſecured them from doing their intended Miſchief.</hi> But ſtill the <hi>Evil Spirit</hi> was not quite laid, in the year 1666 the ſeveral Parties ventured once more upon a <hi>Plot,</hi> to <hi>murther his Majeſty, Overthrow the Government, ſurprize the Tower, kill the Lord General, and to Fire the City of</hi> London; <hi>which Plot was to have been executed</hi> September <hi>the</hi> 3d <hi>of that year; Mony was distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the Conſpirators, and a Council of the Heads ſettled at</hi> London <hi>for the management of Affairs; for which Helliſh Plot</hi> Rathbone, Saunders, Tucker, Flint, Evans, Myles,<note place="margin">London Gazet, Apr. 26. 1666.</note> Weſcot <hi>and</hi> Cole, <hi>were Arraign'd, Condemn'd and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted.</hi> And though ſo many ſuffer'd, one part of the Plot was unhappily effected in that <hi>dreadful Conflagration wherein the great Metropolis of the Kingdom was laid in Aſhes.</hi> This diſappointed, the <hi>Devil of Sedition</hi> flew into <hi>Scotland,</hi> where in the ſame Year the <hi>Old Covenanters</hi> broke out into a <hi>Rebellion</hi> at <hi>Pentland Hills,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ravill. red. p. 3.</note> but were ſoon happily diſperſs'd by his Majeſties Forces; ſoon after <hi>James Mitchel,</hi> a <hi>Covenanting Miniſter,</hi> attempted the <hi>Aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of Dr. <hi>Sharp,</hi> the <hi>most Reverend Archbiſhop of St. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> and in the attempt mortally wounded the <hi>Biſhop of Orkney,</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 33.</note> for which Fact <hi>confest and prov'd</hi> he was deſervedly Executed <hi>Jan.</hi> 18. 1677. But the poor <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> eſcap'd not ſo, <hi>implacable Fanaticiſm</hi> purſued till he was effectually <hi>Murder'd</hi> by ſome of the Crew with the <hi>moſt inexpreſſible Barbarity,</hi> May 3. 1679. The ſame Month a <hi>new Rebellion</hi> under the <hi>Banner of the Covenant</hi> broke out at <hi>Bothwell Bridge,</hi> where their Powers were cruſht once again; from <hi>which blow God grant they may never more recover:</hi> But all theſe Ill ſucceſſes have not yet it ſeems ſo ram'd our nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous <hi>Sectaries</hi> and their <hi>Favourers;</hi> but that <hi>Religious Treaſon</hi> has once more made its Entry among us, <hi>The King himſelf, the Duke, the great Officers of State, the Loyal
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95396:28"/>Magiſtrates of the City of</hi> London, <hi>all doom'd to Slaughter, and the Government both in Church and State to Ruine.</hi> I may uſe the Words of his MAJESTY's Declaration in the caſe,<note place="margin">Kings Declar. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>It's hard to imagine how men of ſo different Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſts and Opinions could joyn in any Enterprize; but it is certain they readily concurr'd in the Reſolution of taking Arms to deſtroy the Government, even before they had agreed what to ſet up in the place of it.</hi> But the <hi>Samaritans</hi> in the Text would ſerve for a Pattern, who though Idolaters of very different kinds, could all agree in the deſign to ruine the reſtor'd <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if we reflect upon thoſe <hi>deſires of admittance to publick Preaching</hi> in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which being rejected produced theſe <hi>violent effects,</hi> though they more <hi>baſely</hi> than the <hi>Samaritans, Courted the meaneſt of the of the People,</hi> endeavouring to <hi>inveigle them</hi> into their Party; yet if we remember, that the <hi>Fathers of our Church</hi> had liv'd in a <hi>long Baniſhment</hi> from their Charges, or under the <hi>Cruel influences of rampant Rebellion and Hypocriſie,</hi> whilſt theſe <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> theſe <hi>ravening Wolves</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd the <hi>fat of our Land,</hi> and had engroſs'd to themſelves the <hi>Eſtates of other men,</hi> it ſeems as if they were in the <hi>Samaritans condition,</hi> more fit to manage the <hi>Chargeable deſign</hi> of reinthroning God in his Church than <hi>theſe poor and neceſſitous Exiles;</hi> they offer'd largely for <hi>liberty</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found us once again, and to enjoy their <hi>lawleſs <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations,</hi> no leſs than 500000 <hi>l.</hi> at once to an <hi>empty Treaſury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Myſtery of Nonconformity, p. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> with which Sum, ſince 'twas not accepted, they might eaſily hire <hi>Councellors</hi> of all kinds againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to obſtruct its ſettlement; all which failing, <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Treaſon</hi> were the laſt means left, of which, as I have ſhew'd you, they have made frequent Trials.</p>
            <p>See here then the <hi>Reſult of tender Conſciences,</hi> as they are ſtil'd, and a <hi>Jeſuitical pretence to Moderation;</hi> I have heard it objected by <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> That the Perſons concern'd in the <hi>preſent Plot</hi> were all <hi>Churchmen,</hi> but the Plot it ſelf confutes the Fancy, it being <hi>to deſtroy the Church,</hi> as now ſettled, as well as the State. But I know many <hi>pretend to the Church, frequent Prayers, receive Sacraments,</hi> who yet can readily Vote, <hi>That the Execution of Penal Laws
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95396:28"/>againſt Schiſmaticks is a grievance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Kings Declar. Apr. 8. 1681. p. 5.</note> and lay a good founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for a future Schiſmatical Plot, by reſolving, <hi>That if His Majeſty ſhould come by any violent Death, it ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged upon the Papiſts.</hi> That Aſſertion of <hi>Colledge</hi>'s looks very odly, <hi>That the laſt Parliament at</hi> Weſtminſter—<hi>in</hi> —81, <hi>was of the ſame Opinion with that in</hi>— 40:<note place="margin">Colledges Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, p. 81, 82.</note> Some tell us, that the Members of that Parliament were all <hi>Churchmen</hi> too: but what they were their <hi>Horrid Actions</hi> declar'd, and their <hi>Mortal Hatred</hi> to the Government of the <hi>Church</hi> evidences the falſhood of that Opinion, <hi>Such Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men the true Church of</hi> England <hi>will always diſown, as only fit Aſſociates for Conſpirators and Rebels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thanks be to God the <hi>Snare is now broken,</hi> and we are thus far <hi>deliver'd;</hi> God has watch'd over us when we were too ſecure, and by his Providence has laid open <hi>the Myſtery of that Hypocriſie</hi> which has ſo long impos'd upon us. Would not any <hi>ſober Diſſenter,</hi> when he ſees thoſe who are of his own Perſwaſion run into ſuch <hi>Scandalous Crimes,</hi> begin to queſtion the <hi>Principles he himſelf acts upon?</hi> Is this the <hi>True Proteſtancy</hi> ſome have boaſted ſo much of? or are all <hi>Popiſhly affected</hi> who declare an <hi>Hearty abhorrence of all ſuch Deviliſh Principles and Practices?</hi> May we all bear that <hi>reproachful Character,</hi> rather than for a <hi>Popular Title</hi> run headlong to the Devil; Let us never be <hi>gull'd</hi> into a perſwaſion, that <hi>ſuch Perſons are fit to build up our Church againſt the Aſſaults of Ignorance, Idolatry, Profaneneſs or Superſtition;</hi> but rather let us unite cloſely among our ſelves. Let all Perſons who profeſs <hi>Loyalty to their Sovereign,</hi> be <hi>truly Loyal to that God who is the great Preſerver of Princes;</hi> Let the World be convinced, that even thoſe <hi>ſeeming Vertues</hi> which render <hi>Schiſmaticks plauſible,</hi> are <hi>ſolid and real in all thoſe who maintain Gods Ancient, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and Regular Worſhip;</hi> Let us <hi>Fear God,</hi> and <hi>Honour and Truſt our Sovereign;</hi> Let no <hi>ſubtile Emiſſaries of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> make us <hi>Suſpicious of our Superiours</hi> or <hi>of one another;</hi> That ſo we preſerving the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the bond of peace and righteouſneſs of life, the work of God may proſper in our hand;</hi> That all Plots and Treaſons may for ever be execrated, and all <hi>England</hi> may hear and fear, and no ſuch Wickedneſs may be heard of among us any more.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:95396:29"/>
               <hi>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, be render'd as is moſt due, all Honour, Glory, Praiſe, Power, Majeſty and Dominion, from henceforth and for evermore.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95396:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
